<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moste profitable and commendable science, of surueying of landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes: drawen and collected by the industrie of Valentyne Leigh. Whereunto is also annexed by the same authour, a right necessarie treatise, of the measuryng of all kyndes of lande, be it meadow, pasture, errable, wood, hill, or dale, and that aswell by certaine easie, and compendious rules, as also by an exact and beneficiall table, purposely drawen and deuised for that behalfe</title>
            <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842467</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7121</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moste profitable and commendable science, of surueying of landes, tenementes, and hereditamentes: drawen and collected by the industrie of Valentyne Leigh. Whereunto is also annexed by the same authour, a right necessarie treatise, of the measuryng of all kyndes of lande, be it meadow, pasture, errable, wood, hill, or dale, and that aswell by certaine easie, and compendious rules, as also by an exact and beneficiall table, purposely drawen and deuised for that behalfe</title>
                  <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Kingston] for Andrew Maunsell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ I-Q⁴.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Surveying --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MOSTE PROFITABLE AND commendable ſcience, of Suruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Landes, Tenementes, and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes: Drawen and Collected by the Induſtrie of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne Leigh.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is alſo annexed by the ſame Authour, a right ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie Treatiſe, of the meaſuryng of all kyndes of Lande, be it Meadow, Paſture, Errable, wood, Hill, or Dale, and that aſwell by certaine eaſie and compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Rules, as alſo by an exact and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall Table, purpoſely drawen and deuiſed for that behalfe.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Maunſell.</p>
            <p>Anno Domini. 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:2"/>
            <head>Valentine Leighe to the <hi>gentle Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eyng that J doe novve at this tyme entreate, not of any vaine fable or triflyng toye, but of ſuche earneſt and ſerious matter, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the profite of moste men, and the benefite and commoditie of eche maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone: J humbly beſeche all men (inaſmuche, as the thyng it ſelf, appertaineth to euery manne) that in readyng thereof, thei vvill vouchſafe, to harken, attribute, and graunte, ſuche diligent and vvillyng eare, mynde, and attention, as thei are accustomed, and vſe to doe, in thoſe, or ſuche caſes, vvhiche thei accoumpt moste vvaightie, graue, and neceſſarie; &amp; vvhiche thei are moſte deſirous to knovv, learne and vnderstande. And firſte, let this one thyng, bee vvell pondered emongeste you, vvho is it of vs all, that hauyng any thing (vvhatſoeuer it be) vvhich maie bee made double or treble more profitable, to hym by good gouernemente, vſage, and ouerſighte thereof, then the ſame is at this preſent, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer it to runne to loſſe, and decaie, then he vvould once (by giuyng a little earneste attentiue
<pb facs="tcp:7121:3"/>
diligence) read, heare, and vnderſtande the meanes by vvhiche he maie, or might, not onely better the thyng vvhiche he poſſeſſeth, but alſo thereby ſo muche encreaſe his aduauntage, grovvyng by the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſeyng the ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Surueiyng of landes, is the matter, vvherupon this preſent booke entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, vvhiche teacheth the gouernmente of the Mannours, landes and tenementes of eche perſone, and hovv to make a perfecte Surueye of the ſame, to moste profite. And alſo, hovv to engroſſe your terrors and Rentalls thereof. And finally, hovv to meaſure all kindes of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, be it Meadovv, Paſture, Errable, VVoodde, ill, or dale, &amp; in vvhat forme or figure ſo euer it is fashioned, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly lieth, vvith the forme, hovv to vnderstande the contentes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, aſvvell by a beneficiall Table, already &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made for that behalfe, as othervviſe by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Rules to the ſame appertainyng. All vvhiche thinges, I haue (gentle Reader) not vvithout pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauell for thy commoditie, hereafter deſcribed.</p>
            <p>J ſhall therefore, for my revvard, or recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe thereof requeſt no more at your handes, for my trauell therein, but onely, that it maie pleaſe you, to
<pb facs="tcp:7121:3"/>
take my poore good vvill, and intente in thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parte, and the rather, becauſe J humbly ſubmit my vvhole vvorke, vnto the correction of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if J haue (by ouerſight or othervviſe) mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the matter.</p>
            <p>And although ſome perchaunce ſhall thinke, thei could haue doen the ſame muche better then J haue doen, J vvill not muche contende, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyng and grauntyng thereof. But yet ſeyng I am one of the first, that attempted the collectyng of the ſame Arte into a volume, to the publication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for the benefite of the common vvealthe, J doe not mistruste, but euery indifferent perſone, vvill thinke theſe my labours (ioyned vvith ſome ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and taken in hande for his instruction) at the leaste vviſe, ſo muche vvorthe, as the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of a bare good vvorde, and frendlie reporte: alvvaies remembryng, that although moste men, can perhappes amende a deuiſe once begun, yet that euery first deuiſe, in euery thyng, is moste harde, &amp; troubleſome: and therefore albeit here novv, not ſo exquiſitely handled in euery point at the first, as it maie be hereafter, beyng (as the Prouerbe ſaith) muche eaſier to amende, then to inuente: yet I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie
<pb facs="tcp:7121:4"/>
praie thee, not by carpyng or othervviſe, to depraue the aucthors honeſt meanyng. And J aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thee, by this thy frendlie acceptation of theſe firste fruites of my ſimple ſtudies, thou maieſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce ſo animate my vvillyng mynde, that thou ſhalt gaine to thy ſelf thereby, the fruition and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, of my other like ſtudies in ſuche behalfe. And thus I can ſaie no more, but vviſhe euery man aſmuche profite, and benefite in readyng here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as my vvillyng attempte herein hath entended them. And ſo J ende bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng thee gentle Reader moſte hartely vvell to fare.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This .xxvij. of October. Anno Christi. 1562.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7121:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The true and moſte liuely and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte deſcription, and inſtruction, of the moſt</hi> neceſſarie and commendable Science of <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiyng of Landes: drawne and deuiſed <hi>by the induſtrie of</hi>
               </hi> Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne Leighe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as Landes and Tenementes, and like reuenewes of enheritance are the cheef and moſte principall liuelode, and ſuretie of liuyng, that any perſone or perſones, of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of degrees whatſoeuer, haue or ſtande ſeaſed of, or poſſeſſed, in this life: Euen ſo, the Surueiyng, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernyng, and prudent improuyng, preſeruyng, augmentyng, and guidyng of the ſame, is the moſte waightie, profitable, and neceſſarie function, or office, that any perſone can haue, or ought chéefly and circumſpectly to prouide for, as the meane and onely thyng by whiche, and of the whiche, euery maner of perſone, yea, with his wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and family (if thei haue any) while thei be in this world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are ſuſtained and maintained: and therefore, the ſame is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other thynges, requiſite moſte vigilantly to bee ſought for, learned and knowen.</p>
            <p>And like alſo, as euery other Science, or Arte, hath ſome ſpecial rules and groundes, vpon whiche the whole Science dependeth. Euen ſo alſo, this facultie hath his diſtincte natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall principles, vpon the due vnderſtandyng, and obſeruyng wherof, all the reſidue of the Science or office, or in any wiſe thereto appertainyng, conſiſteth and is grounded.</p>
            <p>It behoueth therefore hym, whoſoeuer coueteth to bee a good and perfecte Surueiour (either of his owne landes, or other mennes) ſpecially to note and conſider, that in takyng, or makyng of euery Suruey of any Honour, Lordſhip, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:6"/>
Borough, Village or Hamlette, or other Landes, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, or hereditamentes, he ought diligently to obſerue the preceptes and inſtructions hereafter mencioned, whiche doe declare not onely the perfecte maner and forme, firſte of vewyng and Surueiyng the ſame, but alſo (the ſame ſo Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed) how to penne, keepe, ſet out, order, enter, and engroſſe the ſeuerall bookes of Suruey, Terrours, and Rentalles of the ſame, euery one in their due order and forme, without any diſorder or confuſion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore you ſhall vnderſtande, that there be tenne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Principles, or Rules, to bee had in memorie, whiche are theſe that doe orderly enſue.</p>
            <div n="1" type="rule">
               <head>¶The firste Principle, or Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuche as euery maner or parcell of Lande, that is called a Mannour, is not properly or naturally a Mannour, except it haue thoſe thynges that doeth make a Mannour: It is therefore moſte neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that he whiche will bee a good Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiour, doe vnderſtande, whiche bee the ſpeciall notes and grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, by whiche he maie, or ſhall know or diſcerne, whiche is properly a true, and verie Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour, and whiche not. That he doe not wrongfully tearme that to bee a Mannour, that of it ſelf is none <hi>(&amp; e conuerſo)</hi> that to bee none, whiche in verie deede is a Mannour. I haue therefore drawen this breef encloſed deſcription, and definition of a Mannour here now nexte and immediatly followyng, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and enſtructe you, bothe what is naturally a Mannour, and alſo the diuiſion and partes of the ſame, that ye maie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, euen at the eye, perceiue the ſame deſcribed plainly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:6"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The true deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Mannor.</hi>
                  </note>Euery Mannour, that is properly a Mannour, muſt firſte be knowen to haue been called and vſed as a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſince before tyme of memorie of man. For no man can make a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at this daie, ne ioyne twoo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Mannours in one, though the one were decaied, and that the Lorde would bryng the tenauntes of bothe to one Courte, and make but one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of bothe, or aſſigne one Bailie or Collectour for bothe, or let the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall values of bothe, be aunſwered in one miniſters particular acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte, yet in nature thei are, and euer ſhall continue twoo diſtincte Mannours at the common Lawe, what waie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Lorde can, or would take for the ioynyng of them, by the better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of moſte learned in the Lawe, vnleſſe the one Mannour doeth hold of an other, and that the Mannour, whiche ſo doeth holde of the other, doe excheate to the Lorde, and ſo by that meanes it maie be vnited, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the other, and ſo bothe of theim reduced into one Mannour. And more ouer note ſpecially, that euery Mannour hath properly, and naturally theſe three ſeuerall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall thynges enſuyng (in the righte margente hereof) whiche alwaies make it a Mannour, or els can it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be properly a Mannour.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:7"/>
                  <head>videlicet</head>
                  <item>Landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, rentes, ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, that be par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell in Demeaſne, and thei dooe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<list>
                        <item>Euery Scite of any Mannour, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme called the Halle place, or Courte lodge, or Mannour houſe, and alſo the Demeaſne landes, thereto of old time belongyng, be thei reſerued ſtill in the Lordes hande, or lette out to any Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte or Tenaunces by Copie, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, or otherwiſe. And thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are euer properlye Demaines, whiche the lorde of any Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour hath tyme out of mynde of manne vſed, to kepe in his owne handes, or continual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to manure or occupie them with his Mannour houſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, rentes, ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that are percell in ſeruice, and thei containe,
<list>
                        <item>All maner of rentes of aſſiſe, of Frehold, or Cuſtumarie, or Copiholde landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes whiche are parcell of the Mannour, and yet no Demeane landes, and theſe (and alſo Demai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) are deuided into three natures of rentes. <hi>Videlicet.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Rente ſeruice</item>
                              <item>Rente ſacke.</item>
                              <item>Rente charge</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alſo a Court Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron at the leaſte, a Mannour oughte to haue, if it haue a Lete, or Lawday to it, then is it of more efficacie, and to a Court doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine perquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and caſualties whiche are theſe.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fines Terrarum.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Amerciament. Cur.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Herriott. cuſtumar.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Releuia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Wauiat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Straia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Forisfactur.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Eſcact.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Proficua plitm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Curie</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Baronis, autlete.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Curie trium Septimanarum. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:7"/>
                  <head>Theſe thynges alſo are, or commonlie maie bee, belongyng, or appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte, regardaunte, or appendaunt, alſo goyng out, repried, or deducted, of, or to any Mannour or Lordſhippe, and yet the lacke of them, or hauyng of theim, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer make, or els vnmake any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</head>
                  <item>Wardes, Marriages, Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, fréegiftes, or Preſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Nominations, or Aduouſons of Parſonages, Vicarages, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells annexed, free Chappelles, Prebendes, &amp;c. Alſo Villaines, Neifes, and their ſequeles, &amp;c. Commons of Paſture, Moores, marſhes, frewarre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, effouers &amp;c. Cuſtomes, liberties, fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſies, and priueledges.</item>
                  <item>Alſo repriſes of all kindes that is to ſaie, yerely rente reſolute, paimentes, or deductions. Suite of Court, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thes or ſeruices go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or repried out of any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or landes, to any other Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour or Landes, or Perſone or Perſones.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="rule">
               <head>¶The ſeconde Principle or Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Econdarily (The firſte rule knowne) hée that will diligently, and perfectly, ſuruey a Mannour, or other Landes, muſte pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conſider, all maner of Rentes, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, profites, and other thinges whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, doth or ought, or may be, belongyng, or appertainyng, to a Mannour, or bee parte, parcell, or membre of a Mannour, or be appendaunt, or regardaunt, to a Mannour or ſuche other landes, or Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And likewiſe what Rentes, Reſolutes, repriſes, or dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, may bee commonly paied, deducted, or yerely repried, out of any Mannour, landes, or teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, to any perſone, or
<pb facs="tcp:7121:8"/>
perſones, or els he can neuer, make any good ſuruey. And for your better inſtruction herein (although I haue partely, in the firſt Rule, briefly touched the ſame) I do now here in this ſeconde Rule, not onely more amply, and diſtinctly, declare the ſame: but alſo plainly, and particulerly deſcribe the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall natures and definitions of euery kynde of thyng, that commonly doth, or can belong to any maner of Landes or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes. And therfore you ſhall vnderſtand, that euery Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Lordſhip or Mannour that is of it ſelf, properly a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it hath commonly, and for the moſte parte, theſe Sixe thinges enſuyng, belongyng to the ſame, that is to ſaie.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1 Rentes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2 Demaynes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3 Perquiſites or caſualties.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4 Thinges appendaunt, and regardant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5 Cuſtomes, Liberties, and Priuiledges.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6 Repriſes reſolute, or deductions.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>And firſt J vvill beginne to declare of all maner Rentes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rentes of Lands, and Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts holden at will.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here maye belonge to a Manour, Rentes of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Tenements, Meſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Burgages, Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Curtillages, Toftes Roueles, Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Douehouſes, barnes, Stables, Gardeines, Orchardes, Parkes, Warrens, Meares, Waters, Pondes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:8"/>Fiſhinges, Meadowes, Cloaſes, Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Fieldes, Paſtures, Woodes, Groues, Heathes, Firzes, Moores, Marſhes, Turba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp;c. Graunted, to any perſone, or perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, at the Lordes pleaſure, or will, for ſome yerely rent, certaine, paiable, at two or fower feaſtes of the yere, vſuall by euen porcions. And ſuche parſons, are commonly called, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes at will, and theſe are remoueable, at the pleaſure, and will of the Lorde, and theſe alſo, commonly are not chargeable, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring their tenementes, or holdynges, but they are puniſheable for waſte, by action of treſpaſſe, if thei commit any in the ſame, and are ſtraineable for their rente.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rentes of Lands and Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts holden for tearme of yeres.</note>There may alſo belong to a Mannour yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rentes, of any Landes, Tenements, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages, &amp;c. (as aforeſaide) that are demiſed, to any perſone or perſones, by Indenture, or without Indenture, or writing (by worde or parolle onely) for tearme of yere, or yeres, for ſome yerely rent, certaine, paiable, at twoo, or fower feaſtes, of the yere, by euen porcions, and ſuche parſons, are called Tenauntes, for tearme of yeres, and are bound, to ſuche repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racions, and other duties, as the couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or promiſes in their leaſes doe containe, and they are chargeable with waſte, if they doe commit any, and are ſtrainable, for their rent of common right, or maye bee iuſtly ſued for the ſame, by action of debte if it be arrere. And ſuche are not bounde to appeare vpon Iuries at Weſtminſter, nor at Aſſiſes or Seſſions, vnleſſe they may Diſpende .xl. s. of
<pb facs="tcp:7121:9"/>Fréehold otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rentes of freeholde Landes.</note>Alſo, there may belong to a Mannour, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Fréeholders, that holde their landes, Tenementes, or hereditamentes, of the lorde of the Mannour, ſome in Capite, by knights ſeruice, eſcuage vncertaine, or Graundſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geauntie, and ſome by Soccage or Burgage tenure, by paiyng yerely a Roſe, a pounde of Pepper, or Capons, Hennes, or ſuche like, and ſome (both the Fréeholders) Tenauntes in Capite, and Tenauntes in ſoccage) paie a yerely rent beſides their ſeruices, and ſome time no Rent. And ſuche Landes and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp;c. thei haue to them and to their hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and the ſame is commonly called Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and thoſe Tenauntes and Tenauntes for tearme of life, are alwaies called Fréehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And ſometyme alſo, they holde by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Seruices. And euery ſuche Tenaunt, oweth fealtie to their chiefe lorde. And ſuche Tenauntes alwaies, if thei maye diſpende by their ſaid Tenementes, xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. a yere or aboue, are likewiſe chargeable vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuries at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minſter hall, and at Aſſiſſes, and Seſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and may alſo impleade, and be impleaded (if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo require) for their Tenementes, at the courtes at Weſtminſter without the lordes licence as aforeſaied. But ſuche Tenauntes are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly chargable with waſt, if they doe any vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſaid fréeholde tenementes, tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for terme of life onely excepted. And you muſt note there are ſondry kindes of frée holders. Some hold their lande by Charter, ſome by newe Feoffamente, and ſome by olde
<pb facs="tcp:7121:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tenure, and by many maner of rents, Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſeruices. And ſome be Tenauntes in fée ſimple, and ſome Tenauntes in taile, and many ſuche like, and may holde their Landes by diuers cuſtomes, ſeruices and tenures, as by homage and fealtie, and as I ſaid before by knightes ſeruice, graundſergeanty, petieſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geauntie, eſcuage, Frankalmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, Homage au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſtrell, tenure in Soccage, Burgage, and villanage: for the further knowledge wherof, I referre you to maiſter Littleton. And note alſo, that the Lorde of ſuche Tenauntes, if he haue any rentes, cuſtomes or ſeruices, detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from him, whiche he can by any euidence, rentals or Court Rolles, proue a poſſeſſion therof, in himſelf, or his Aunceſtors ſince the limitation, in the ſtatute of Weſtminſter, the ſecond: Then hee may lawfully diſtraine for the ſame. And theſe Tenaunts be ſtraineable by their Lordes, if their Rentes or ſeruices be arrere, vnpaied, or vndon. And alſo a writ of Ceſſauit, lieth againſt them, if occaſion ſo ſerue. Alſo the Lorde maie haue a writ of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheate, if any ſuche tenaunt doe commit felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or dye without Heires generall, or ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. And ſuch Tenaunts, doe commonly paie, a releefe to the Lorde at euery alienation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge or death of any tenaunt of the ſame. And note alſo, there may be alſo forrain frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, whiche holde not of the Mannour, and yet holde of the Lorde. And it is further to be ſpecially remembred, that all ſuche Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes as holde any Landes, tenementes or hereditamentes by charter, déede, or Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:10"/>for the tearme of their owne liues, or by <hi>le curtyze de angleterre,</hi> or for the tearme of a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother mans life, are alwaies Fréeholders.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rentes of Lands hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane.</note>There may bee alſo belongyng to a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, rentes of Landes, tenements and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, holden of the Mannour, by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, called auncient Demeaſne. And in ſome places the whole Mannour is Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Demeaſne. And the tenaunts alſo paie ſome a Roſe, ſome a pound of Pepper, ſome Capons, ſome Hennes, and ſuche like, both with an yerely rent in money, and ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a rent, and by certaine homage, and feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuche ſeruices. And the Tenauntes of ſuche Landes and tenementes, haue the ſame to them and their Heires, accordyng to the cuſtome of auncient demeaſne. And ſuch Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes can not impleade or bee impleaded for their Landes or tenements, in any other court, but in the Lordes courte of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, without the Lordes licence. And theſe Tenauntes, are not chargeable vpon Iuries at Weſtminſter, or at Aſſiſes, or Seſſions, vnleſſe they may diſpende other freehold lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of xl. s. a yere. Theſe Tenauntes alſo, are ſtraineable, if their rentes be arrere. If they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit waſte, they forfeite their Tenauntries by their cuſtome. Theſe Tenaunts, paie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly at euery alienation, death or exchange, a fine certayne, by their cuſtome. In ſome Mannours ſuche Landes are heritable, in ſome Mannours not.</p>
                  <p>There may be alſo belongyng, to a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Rentes of other Landes, Tenementes,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:10"/>Meſuages, Cottages, &amp;c. (as aforeſaid) that are cuſtomary and demiſed to any Tenaunts of the ſame Mannour, by copy of court rolle, at the will of the Lorde, accordyng to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Mannour there, either by the verge, rodde, or otherwiſe. And in ſome Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, the tenauntes, holde their ſaide cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to theim and to their heires, in fée Simple, or in fée tayle, by copy of court Rolle, and in ſome Mannours, for tearme of yeres, and in ſome Mannours for tearme of thrée liues, accordyng as the cuſtome of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mannour hath bene tyme out of mynde of man vſed. And theſe lands, be properly called Copie holdes or cuſtomarie tenements. And in ſome place they bee called olde aſter lands. And in Somerſetſhire, Deuonſhire, Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal, Dorſetſhire and Gloceſterſhire (where moſt Mannours haue commonly thoſe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie<note place="margin">Rente ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice which is properly all ſuch lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as are holden of the lord by Fealty, and certaine rent, or by homage, Fealty, and Rent, or by any other ſeruice, and certaine rent, of which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are theſe, of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie Landes and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by copie of Courte Roll at will, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp;c.</note> Landes. (ſuche landes and Tenements are there called Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines) and theſe cannot impleade or be impleaded, for their tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes out of the Lordes courte, of the Mannour whereof they are holden without the Lordes licence, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they chargeable vpon Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at Weſtminſter, nor at Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or Seſſions, vnleſſe they may alſo diſpend other fréehold, of xl.s. yerely or aboue. Alſo if theſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes commit waſte, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly forfeite their landes, to the<note place="margin">Rentes</note> Lorde. And theſe tenaunts cannot
<pb facs="tcp:7121:11"/>ſell, alienate nor exchaunge, their Landes by Déede, Fine, or Feoffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But muſt ſurrender the ſame into the Lordes handes before the Stewarde (or in ſome place in the preſence of twoo other Tenaunts of the Mannour) to the vſe of hym or theim that ſhall haue the ſame la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, be it in fée ſimple, fée taile, for tearme of life or yeres, accordyng to the cuſtome of the ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And that perſone that ſhould haue it, muſte in the Courte take of the Lorde or his Stewarde, the ſame Landes and Tenementes ſo ſurrendred And theſe Tenauntes are euer alſo ſtraineable, if their Rentes bee arrere. And they alſo paie commonly at euery alienatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, death, or exchaunge, and ſurrender of their Tenements a fine (in ſome Mannours certaine and knowen) but in moſte Mannours vncertain and at the Lordes will, as he or his Surueiour, or his Stewarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng thereto auctoriſed, pleaſeth to aſſeſſe the ſame, with the agrement of the Tenaunt that taketh it. And in moſte Mannours theſe Landes are heritable. And note ſpeciallie for a generall Rule, that there may bee of Cuſtomarie, or Copie holde Lande, all maner of like eſtates, as there maye hee, of free holde lande,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:11"/>at the common lawe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rentes of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie lande, holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by cuſtome called tenaunt right.</note>There are alſo Rentes, of muche like nature, of cuſtomary and copie holde Landes, and Tenementes belongyng to Mannours, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places, and ſpecially in the Counties of Yorke, Weſtmerland Cumberlande, Cheſter, Lancaſter, and the Biſhopricke of Durham, and ſome other Counties, dimiſed alſo accordyng to the Cuſtome of ſuche Mannours, to the tenauntes of the ſame, in ſome places to hold to theim and their heires, and next of kinne, ſo long as there is any of the ſame ſtocke, kinred or linage remainyng. And in ſome Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but onely ſo long, as there is any lefte of the name, and they commonly call ſuche holdinges in thoſe places, Tackes, and in ſome other places, they are called Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte rightes. And theſe alſo can not impleade, or be impleaded out of the Lordes Court, of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for their Landes or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without the Lords licence, nor are chargeable vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ries, at Weſtminſter, or at Aſſiſes, or Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, excepte they maye diſpende yerely xl. s. of other freeholde land, as is aforeſaide. Theſe alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly by their cuſtome, forfeite to
<pb facs="tcp:7121:12"/>the Lord, their Tackes or Holdin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, if thei commit any waſt. They are alſo ſtrainable for their rents, if they be arrere. And the Fines (v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery exchaunge or death of tenaunts is in fewe of thoſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours alſo, certaine and knowen. But in moſte of thoſe Mannours, vncertaine, and to be aſſeſſed, as the Lorde or his Officer, and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt can agree for the ſame. And commonly alſo their ſaid Tackes, Tenaunt rightes or holdings are heritable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorandum,</hi> no maner of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, can make his Landes, Copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, or Cuſtumarie at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente daye, vnleſſe the ſame haue bene cuſtumarie lande tyme out of mind of man vſed. But a man may make Copiholde, freehold, euen at this daie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorandum,</hi> Alſo there may be, belonging to a Mannour in one ſhire or place, yea and parcel of the ſame Mannour, diuers landes and tenementes in other Tounes, and ſometyme in other Counties, a greate diſtance from the Mannor, and aunſwerable, and to be valued in the value, or accoumpte of the ſame Mannour, and as parcell of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>And now that I haue treated of
<pb facs="tcp:7121:12"/>Rentes, of Landes and tenements, and hereditamentes at large, in a generalitie, whiche doe or may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a Mannour, I will nowe touche in a ſpecialtie the nature of certaine Rentes, of ſeueral names or kindes which are contained al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the compaſſe of the Rentes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue generally declared, and yet, for your better inſtruction) hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter particulerly touched, whiche are theſe enſuing, and ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments &amp; her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bagij.</hi>
                     </note>Rent of Iuiſtement, or herbage, is where a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt holdeth, or occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieth onelie the feeding, graſing, or paſture, of a Parke, or anye other grounde, paled, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloaſed, wherein anye Deare, or ſuche like are: and commonly the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch Iuiſtement or herbage in ſome place muſte put but a nomber of cattaill certaine, and at ſome ſpeciall times of the yere, and perchaunce but the Tenauntes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the Mannor one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; in ſome other place the Tenaunt may put in beaſtes ſaunce number,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:13"/>and when hee will, and yeldeth a yerely rent for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſcun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> generis.</hi>
                     </note>Rent of milles, is where the Lorde of a Mannour hath belongynge to his Mannour any maner of corne milles, horſmilles, watermilles, windemil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or quarnes for grain or other milles, as ſmith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milles, yron milles, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng milles, Sieth mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, cutler milles, Tinne blaſte milles, Lead blaſte milles, or ſuche like, and hath lett the ſame to hys Tenaunt, at a Rente, or hath demiſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Socome, which is the grindyng of his cuſtomarie Tenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Corne, at his Corne mille to any perſon for a yerely rent, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum &amp; feni.</hi>
                     </note>Rente of Corne, or Hay, is where the Lorde hath graunted any Landes, or Tenementes to his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, yelding the yerely rent of ſome certaine no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of corne, or Haie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is properly, where a Tith is impropriated, to a Mannour, and the
<pb facs="tcp:7121:13"/>Lorde hath demiſed the ſame to his Tenaunt at a rente.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note>Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Fiſhings, is wher the Lord of a Mannour, hath demiſed to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, any Weares, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, or ſuche like in any Creeke, Riuer, Meare, Poole, pond, or common Sewer or ſeueral water, or ſuche like, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fiſhyng called the Kettels at the ſea ſide, or the dredgyng of Oyſters, Muſkels or Cockles in any Crekes, or other places, within his Mannour, at a yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rente reſerued, for the ſame. And note, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fiſhe the ſeuerall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lorde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lordes licence, the Lorde may bring his action againſt the partie, vppon the ſtatute Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter the firſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnorum.</hi>
                     </note>Rent of Swannes, or for Swannes, is where the Lorde hath great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, Meares or fennes, and hath Swannes bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng within the precinct of his Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour, and hath
<pb facs="tcp:7121:14"/>demiſed them to a tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a yerely rente reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: this rent is muche in vre in Lincolneſhire, Cambridgeſhire, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The like Rente, maie be and in ſome Mannours, is of Herneſhawes, Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelors. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note>Rent of Mines, is where the Lord of a Mannour, hath demiſed any Mines of Tinne, Lead, Copper, or Coale to anye of hys tenauntes, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing a yerely Rente, out of the ſame, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuche like Mines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rium.</hi>
                     </note>Rente of Quarries, is where the Lord of a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, hath likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed anye Quarires of Free ſtone, Harde ſtone, or of Marble, Slate, Whetſtones, or ſuche like, or of Grauel, Sand or Chalke, or ſuche like to any Tenaunte, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to hym out of the ſame an yerely rente.</p>
                  <p>Muche like this rent, is the Rente of a peece of ground hauyng ſlimy or Clayie Earthe, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:7121:14"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rentes of all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi>
                     </note>Bricke &amp; Tyle is made, when it is let to a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt at an yerely rente. Rent of frée Warre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is where the lorde of a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, hath in his Parke, Wodds, Heathes, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or other grounds, waſt or ſeueral, any War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of Conies, Hares, Herneſhawes, or anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaſtes, or foules, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he either kepe the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in his owne handes, or demiſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to any parſon, at a yerely Rent.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum Warren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium.</hi>
                     </note> And note, that if any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon kill anye ſuche his game, within the Lords ground, the Lorde maie haue an action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt hym, at the common lawe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorandum,</hi> no man can haue a frée Warren, but he haue the ſame, by the Kynge, or Quéenes ſpeciall graunt of Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, except it haue bene v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed time out of mynd and allowed before Iuſtices of Oyer.</p>
                  <p>Annuall rent of pencion, or porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is where, there
<pb facs="tcp:7121:15"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionum &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionum.</hi>
                     </note>is any yerely Rente, or pencion in money, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Portion goyng or growyng due, out of any other lordſhips or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Landes or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Parſonages, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carages or Tithes, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a Mannour, and before time graunted to the ſame Mannour by ſome compoſition, or for ſome liberty of waie, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe, or ſuche like. Some accompte this no Rente.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum.</hi>
                     </note>Rent of workes, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie where the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie Tenauntes, of a Mannour are bounde by their cuſtome to help the lorde in Sowyng tyme, Mowyng tyme, or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſte, ſome with thrée Daies worke, ſome with fower daies worke, ſome with moe, and ſome with leſſe, accordyng to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. And where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde is agreed, or at compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with euery of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes for a yerely rent for the ſame, or els hath demiſed the whole day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works
<pb facs="tcp:7121:15"/>of the whole man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſome one tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, at one certaine and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire yerely rent reſerued, then is ſuche rent called <hi>Redditus operum cuſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Els is it no Rente.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus pro licentijs.</hi>
                     </note>Rent yerely reſerued for licences, is where the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie Tenauntes, by their cuſtome can not let or ſet their landes aboue a yere, or but from three yeres to thrée yeres. And that they giue the Lorde a yerely rente, to licence theim, to lett or ſett the ſame for moe yeres or longer time. And alſo it is where the cuſtomarie tenaunt cannot ſtocke a woodde, or till his Laie ground, without the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des licence, and for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence herof, yeldeth an yerely rent. But in ſome Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nours the Tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts geue but a Fine for the ſame, and no yerely rent.</p>
                  <p>Rent called newe rent, or encreaſe of Rente, is where the Lord hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his Tenauntes, or any of theim to builde or
<pb facs="tcp:7121:16"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nouus Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
                     </note>ſett anye Walle, Barne, ſtalle, or Houſe, vpon any parte of the Lordes waſt, or ſome, or that the Lord hath graunted any Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte to encloaſe anye parte of his common or waſt ground, or ſuch like, and reſerueth to himſelfe an yerely Rente for the ſame and ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> there are ſome kindes of Iſſues, and yerely Profites ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in ſome Mannours, which are not properly called rentes, becauſe of ther vncertaintie, becauſe ſome yere they may bee more, and ſome yere leſſe, and ſuche are theſe foure enſuyng, and their like, and where they are certaine, they are in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of rentes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catuum.</hi>
                     </note>Rent or yerely profite of Faires and Markets is wher there is any Faire kepte within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mannor, once or twiſe a yere, and the Lorde hath demiſed the profites of Bothes, ſtandinges, Tolles, and ſuch like profites, of the Faire, at a rent, to any of his Tenauntes. And in like maner of profites of Bothes, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinges, ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb facs="tcp:7121:16"/>and tolles or other profits of a wekely mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, kept once or twiſe a wéeke within the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Venditio boſcoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſcoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note>Profites of woodſale, is where ſomtymes the LORD of a Mannour doeth make a yerely ſale of his woodes, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme it maie be a yerely rent alſo, when the lorde of a Mannour, hath lett to Fearme at a rente, to ſome of his tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the ſale of a greate Woode, whiche is perchaunce growyng in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or waſte, or ſuche a Wod wherof he kepeth the herbage for hymſelf, or other his tenauntes, and reſerueth an yerely rente, and in like maner maie it bee of Buſhes, Thornes, and gorſſe. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Rent or profit of Heath, Furſes, or Turbarie is euen like, where ſomety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the lorde of a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doeth either make a yerely ſale of the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:17"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Venditio Iampno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere &amp; Turba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>or els let to Fearme the Furſes, Heath, or Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of ſome Moore, or encloſed grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to ſome of his tenauntes, for Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well at a Rente. And in like maner it is in ſome Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nours of Broome, &amp; Fearne, or Brakens. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Panna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</hi>
                     </note>Pannage, is where the lorde of a Mannour hath a Parke, or ſome greate woods, that hath ſtore of Maſte, of Oke, Bech. &amp;c. and hath vſed to take of his tenauntes, for euery of their Swine that ſhal goe there betwene Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas, &amp; Martilmas, in ſome place i. d. a peece, in ſome Mannour ij. d. a péece &amp;c. by his Bailie or Fermer of the ſame Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who either yeldeth a yerely rente therefore, or els a yerely accompte of the ſaied Pannage to the Lorde. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>There maie alſo belong to a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Rent charge, whiche is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie where the Lorde hath alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, or graunted ſome parte of
<pb facs="tcp:7121:17"/>
                     <note place="margin">Rente chardge</note>his Mannour, or Landes, to any perſone and his heires in Fee, by Inde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture enrolled, Fine, or Feoff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, or otherwiſe: Reſeruyng a yerely rent to hymſelf, and his hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, paiable at .ij. or .iiij. Feaſtes of the yere, and in the ſame graunte therof, hath put a prouiſo, or clauſe of diſtreſſe, that he maie lawfullie diſtraine, if the Rent bee arrere, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any feaſt of paiment, in whiche it ſhalbe due. Alſo euery Fée ferme, where the Lorde maie diſtraine for his rent, if it be vnpaied, is a Rent chardge. And a rent chardge can in no wiſe be apportioned, if the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tée or his heires, doe purchaſe any of thoſe landes, that are chardged with ſuche rente: the grauntee and his heires may be chardged in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone for this rente, vnleſſe there be expreſſe woordes in the Deede by prouiſo made to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary therof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rent ſecke</note>There may alſo belong to a Mannour, Rent Secke, whiche is alwaies where the Lorde or his aunceſtours, Lordes of the ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, haue graunted to any perſon, any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lande, to hym, and his heires, in Fee ſimple, or in fee taile, with remainder ouer to an other in Fee or ſuche like, reſeruyng a ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely Rente. And yet in the ſaied graunte, or writyng thereof made, there bee no clauſe of diſtreſſe, or prouiſo of Reentrie: that the lorde
<pb facs="tcp:7121:18"/>may diſtraine, or reentre for non paiment of the Rente, if it be behinde vnpaide after any feaſt or day of paiment. And therfore it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a drie Rent, becauſe it can not be ſtrained for: And if the perſone and his heires, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Rent, Seche is graunted, or reſerued, had neuer ſeaſon therof, he is as ſome men iudge, nere without his remeadie for recouery ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But if he haue had once ſeaſon thereof, he maie recouer it well enough, by a Writte of nouelle Diſſeaſon at the common lawe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Annuall Rente.</note>There is alſo an other maner of Rent, called annuall Rente, whiche is commonly when a man graunteth to an other by Deede, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie of x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. a yere, or ſuche like, more or leſſe. And that there is in the Deede, no lande charged, with, or for, the paiment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This rente is neither Rente charge, rente ſeruice, nor Rente ſecke: (and it chargeth the perſone of the graunter, by writte of Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) as ſome mennes opinion is thereof.</p>
                  <p>Demaines, princiyallie is the Mannour place, whiche is ſometyme called the halle place, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the halle courte, ſometyme the Mannour houſe, &amp;c. with all the houſes, buildynges, edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Barnes, ſtables, roomes, courtelages, and yardes, &amp; courtes to the ſame adiacent, or with in any wall, or preciucte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scite of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the Douehouſes, and all Orchardes, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Pondes, Pooles, Motes, Stagnes, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and like places, adioynyng to the Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour
<pb facs="tcp:7121:18"/>houſe, or neare the Scite of the ſame, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly alſo parcell of the Demeanes.</p>
                  <p>Alſo all ſuche Landes, Meadowes, Paſtures, Féedyngs, Cloſes Croftes, and encloſures, as the Lorde of the Mannour, hath commonly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to manure or keepe in his owne handes, or occupation, together with his Mannour place, is alſo commonly parcell of the Demeaſnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Demai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour.</hi>
                     </note>In like maner, a Parke, or any Woodes, or Groues, or any Meares, Riuers, Pondes, or Fiſhynges, maie bee parcell of the Demeanes of a Mannour, if the Lorde or his aunceſtours, haue tyme out of mynde of man, occupied the ſame with his Mannour place.</p>
                  <p>Alſo (ſome exempte) Waſtes, Moores, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, Fennes, and alſo Turbary, which may be parte of the Demaines, if the Lorde haue vſed tyme out of minde, to occupy them in his owne handes.</p>
                  <p>And finallie, for a generall rule, all thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, tenementes, and her editamentes, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly called, knowen, and taken for Demeiſnes whatſoeuer the Lordes of any Mannour, or Lordſhippe, and their aunceſtours haue béen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, tyme out of memorie of man, to occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in their owne handes, with the Mannour place or hedde haile houſe of his Mannour.</p>
                  <p>Memorandum, by the better opinion of the learned in the Law, no Demeaſnes can at this daie, bee demiſed by Copie, but by Indenture,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:19"/>vnleſſe the ſame haue been ſo vſed to be let, time beyonde all mennes remembraunce. <hi>Quaere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fines terraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note>Fines of landes, is commonly where any Copiholde lande falleth into the lordes handes of the Mannour, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his diſpoſition, by death of tenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, excheate, forfeiture, or otherwiſe. And the Lorde or his officer graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame to any Tenaunte, for tearme of three liues, or for yeres, or to hym and his heires, or by tenaunte right, accordyng to the cuſtome of ſuche Mannour, whereof the ſame is holden, and for ſuche cuſtomable re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſeruices as before hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed. And for ſuche eſtate to bee had in the ſame, the Tenaunte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly geueth the lorde, ſome ſumme of money, whiche is called his Fyne. And ſomtyme ſuche cuſtomarie fines in ſome Mannours, are alwaies one, and certaine, and neuer augmented: And in ſome Mannors, their Fynes are moſte commonly vncertaine, and at the choiſe of the Lorde, how much he will take.</p>
                  <p>Alſo when the Lorde of a Mannour letteth a peece of Lande cuſtomarie, or not cuſtomarie, by an Indenture or Leaſe, for tearme of life, or yeres, to any perſon, and reſerueth an yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rente, and taketh a fine, or income
<pb facs="tcp:7121:19"/>for ſuche graunte, or demiſe: the ſame is alſo called <hi>Finis terrarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo where one Copie holder, will, or doeth make ſurrendour of his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemente or holding to an other, and giueth the Lorde a Fyne for the ſame Surrendour, it is alſo called <hi>Finis terrarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo where a Tenaunte giueth the Lorde a Fine, to licence him to Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are his laye grounde, or to let or ſet his cuſtomarie Lande to an other for yeres, by Indenture, or otherwiſe and ſuche like, it is commonly entred emong the title of <hi>Fines terrarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Amerciamentes are alſo parcell of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites of courtes, and are diuerſe, and they are all Summes, Penalties, and mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as, wherein the Tenauntes are amerced, by the Homage or Ferro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, of euerie Courte, Lete, or lawe daie of a Mannour, for lacke of ſuite of Courte, and other ſondrie faultes, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</p>
                  <p>And as when they be Fréeholders, or Copie holders, and owe Suite of courte to a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and make defaulte, or bee abſent at the Lordes Court, and be not there, and be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amerced.</p>
                  <p>And ſome ſuche fréeholders, are at their fine certaine, for their ſuite of Court, and that is called <hi>communis finis,</hi> which common fine is ſet on the heddes of ſuche Suiters, in the
<pb facs="tcp:7121:20"/>margent of the courte Rolle.</p>
                  <p>All other Suiters, that are not at their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Fine for Suite of Courte, are amerced for their abſence, by the title of mia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vppon their heades, in the ſaid margent of the court Rolle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of al ſortes, for Suite of court, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, &amp;c.</note>Likewiſe, when any tenaunte hath bene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the Court, Surueior, Stuarde, and homage, to amende an high way, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire a bridge, or to repaire his cuſtumarie holding, or tenement, by a daie aſſigned, or to auoide ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> parſon, out of his houſe, or to yoke and ring his Swine by a daie vpon forfeiture of a paine and doth it not. And the ſame, at the next court be preſented by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. Then the ſame default is an Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when it is totted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ouer againſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> heades in the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee that gente vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>And Tenauntes being amerced, for not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uing their Mix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns, or dounghilles, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high waie, by a day or for not making their Hedge or Soyſe, by a daie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For not pollyng their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hanging ouer an high waie, and letting carriadge, by a daie, or for not auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>des, or grathoundes by a day (if they cannot Diſpend xl. s. by yere, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute) or for breaking and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yng awaie the Lordes Pales, or hedges, or for Suffering their beaſtes to wander in the highwaie, or to deſtroie the Lordes woddes, or for not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yng open againe by a day, a way by the Tenaunt before wrongfullie encloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uenyng of any ſtreame, brooke or
<pb facs="tcp:7121:20"/>water, out of his right or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> courſe, or for cutting doune, any cuſtumar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> woddes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lordes licence, or for remouing any markes or me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re ſtones. All theſe and manie moe ſuche like, are called Amerciamentes when the Tenauntes are amerced by ſeueral paines with the title of mia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the amerciaments of Bakers, Bruers, Butchers, and Tipplers, for not keping the Aſſiſe, are totted on their heades, with the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of mia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Alſo all ſuche perſons, as do commit fraies, or bloudſheds, in any Manour, and preſented, are amerced with the title of mia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>You muſt ſpecially note, that there are twoo maners of Herriottes one called by the name Heriot Cuſtome, &amp; another called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Herriot Seruice. Herriot ſeruice is euer expreſſed in a mans graunte or déede, and the other is, wheras Herriottes haue béene paied time out of minde by cuſtome. And now to the deſcription of an Herriot.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Parquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties of Courtes, belonging to a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note>An Herriott is properly called the beſt Oxe, Cowe, Horſe, or other thing, that the Lordes Tenaunte holdyng of a Mannour, hath when he dieth. Whiche Herriot after the Tenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes death is commonlie ſeaſed to the Lordes vſe, by the Bailife, Reue, Beadle, or Borſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, of the Mannour, and is commonlie, or ought to bee preſented by the Homage, or<note place="margin">Herriottes</note> ſworne Tenauntes of the Mannour, at the nexte Courte, Lete, or Lawdaie, of the ſame Mannour to be holden.</p>
                  <p>And if the Tenaunte haue no quicke good,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:21"/>then the Lorde will haue the beſte dead good, that his Tenaunt hath when he dieth, for his Heriot.</p>
                  <p>And in ſome Mannours, if the Tenaunte, do voluntarily depart out of his houſe, or ferme, not diſcharged of the Lord, he ſhall paie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord his beſt quicke good, nomine Heriotte. Alſo in ſome Mannours, the Tenaunt ſhall paie his farewell, to the Lorde for his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whiche is called his fare fée, or farewell, and that is in ſome places two ſhillinges, and there alſo the tenaunt muſt before his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doe all maner of reparations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Relieffes.</note>A Relief is after the death, chaunge, or alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of euerie Fréeholder, or of a Tenaunt by auncient demaiſne, and ought to be paied to the lord, as a knowledge. And the relief in ſome place, is the whole yeres Rente of the Fréeholder, or Tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo doyng and in ſome place or Mannour, it is but halfe the yeres rent by cuſtome. A Reliefe is alwaies to bée paied at one whole paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Alſo, for the ſame the Lorde may ſtraine of common right, in euerie parcell of lande, if it be vnpaied.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if a Fréeholder hold of the Lord of the Mannor by knights ſeruice, his Heire being of full age, the Lorde ſhall haue of the Heire for euerie Knightes fée .C. s. noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Releuij. And if the Knightes Fées bee more or leſſe, Then the Tenauntes Relief to bee aportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated thereafter.</p>
                  <p>Waiues, is commonly where a Theefe hath ſtolne certaine goodes, and Cattailles, and brought them into a Mannour, and then by
<pb facs="tcp:7121:21"/>
                     <note place="margin">Waiues.</note>reaſon of purſuite, fléeth awale, leauyng the ſaid goods and cattailes within the iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or circuite of the Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour. And then are thei the lords of that Mannour, and are to be ſeiſed by the Bailife, or Rent there, to the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vſe, and are to bee preſented at the nexte court, to be holden within the ſame Mannor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Straies.</note>Straies, is where any Horſes, Coltes, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xen, Rine, Swine, or other cattailes, do come or ſtraie, and there doe tary one yere, and one daie, and the owner fetche them not, and that the ſame ſtraie haue been Proclaimed, three ſeuerall Sondaies, in three of the nexte Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and three tymes at the nexte markette toune, nexte by the Mannor, then thei are the lords, and thei are alwaies preſentable at the nexte Courte, after the ſtraie happeneth to come into the Mannour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Forfeitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note>Forfeiture, is wheras any tenaunt holdeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Copie holde, or Cuſtomarie Lande of the Lorde of any Mannour, and for non paiment of his rentes, cuſtomes, or ſeruices, or by ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the woodes of his Copie holde, or by lettyng the houſes goe doune, or by makyng waſte, or by alienatyng, lettyng, or ſettyng his cuſtomarie Landes, without the Lordes licence, forfeiteth his Copie holde Lande, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lordes hande, whiche is to be ſo found by the preſentment of the homage, at the next Courte thereto bee holden, and to bee ſeaſed into the Lordes vſe: Alſo tenauntes by deede indented for life, or yeres, maie forfeite their
<pb facs="tcp:7121:22"/>eſtates.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Excheates</note>Excheates is commonlie, where a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of a Mannour committeth Fellonie, then after the Kyng hath had the yere &amp; daie, the Lorde ſhall haue the Lande by Excheate. Likewiſe if a Tenaunt doe dye, without law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heires generall, or ſpeciall, his lande Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheateth to the lorde of the Mannour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſame is holden, and this is commonlie of Free holders, and of Tenauntes by aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente Demeaſne. And the Excheate is alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes to bée preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the homage, at the next courte of the Mannour then to be holden.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Plees and Proceſſe of Courtes.</note>Plees and proceſſes of Courtes, or where the Lorde of a Mannour in his Courte, Lete, or Lawdaie, or three weekes Court, holdeth Plea of his Tenauntes, for their landes hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the ſaied Mannour, or for any debtes, treſpaſſes, or ſommes of money, vnder the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. debte and damage.</p>
                  <p>Memorandum many other thynges maie be accompted, or noumbred emongeſt perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, if the ſame growe but caſuallie, and not yerely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Wardes.</note>Is where any Free holders hold of a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in Capite, Eſcuage, vncertaine, Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſergeauntie, or otherwiſe by knightes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and dieth his heire male, beyng within the age of xxj. yere, and his heire Female be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng within the age of .xiiij. yere. Then the Kyng, or Lorde of the Mannour, or of whom
<pb facs="tcp:7121:22"/>ſuche Lande is holden, oughte to haue the wardeſhippe of ſuche heire: that is to ſaie, the garde, and cuſtodie of the bodie, and landes of ſuche heire, vnto their full age. And alſo the mariage of ſuche heire, if thei happen then to bee vnmaried. And as for the reſidue of the vnderſtandyng of this pointe, I referre you to the inſtruction of the lawe.</p>
                  <p>Patronage of a Churche, is where the Lorde of the Mannour is verie vndoubted patrone of the Parſonage, Vicarage, frée Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp;c. belongyng to his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and maie, or ought to giue the ſame, when, and as often as it falleth voide.</p>
                  <p>Preſentation, is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde maie preſent any lawfull Clerke, to any Parſonage, Vicarege. &amp;c. continually, or but at euery ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or thirde auoidaunce, by force, or in the right of his Mannour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, vicarages, prebendes, Churches. &amp;c.</note>Nomination, is where the lord or any other, maie in the right of his Mannour, or otherwiſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate a condigne Clarke, to any Parſonage, Vicarage &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Aduouſon, is where the Lorde maie, or hath graunted, or giuen his right of preſentyng, or nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natyng
<pb facs="tcp:7121:23"/>
                     <note place="margin">Such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendaunte, regardau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te or exſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante, to a Mannour, are theſe.</note>of a Clarke to any Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or Parſonage, &amp;c. in the life of the Incumbent, or Parſone of the ſame Parſonage, or Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, &amp;c. The ſame graunt or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſon to take place, immediatly vpon, or after the nexte aduoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of the ſame, be it by death, Depriuation, Surrender, or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration of the Parſon, Vicar, or Incumbent of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>And note, the lorde maie grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out twoo, or three Aduouſons of one benefice, the one to take place after the other.</p>
                  <p>Villaines, and Nieffes, is where Bondmen, and Bondwomen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a Mannour, the bondman is called a Villaine, and the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman is called a Nieffe. And in ſome Mannours all the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes are Villaines and Neif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, and then is it ſaied that lande is, a tenure in Villanage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Villaines &amp; Nieffes.</note>Note, the proper Landes of a Villaine and Neiffe, and all his goodes, and cattaills, are the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, to whom he is Villaine, if the Lorde ſo pleaſe, vnleſſe he haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Manumiſſion, or that thei bee enfranchiſed otherwiſe. There are ſometymes Villaines engroſſe, whiche are neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardaunte,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:23"/>nor appendaunte to a Mannour: but the Lorde or his Aunceſtours, haue boughte the ſame and therefore thei are called Villaines engroſſe: their landes, goodes, and cattalls, are likewiſe at the Lordes pleaſure and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
                  <p>And as touchyng other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that be appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunte to a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſome maner of Commons are appendaunte to a Mannour, aſwell as appurtenaunte.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Free Warrens, in ſome place maie bee appendaunte to a Mannour aſwel as appurtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <p>Alſo euery Mannour, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly his peculie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeuerall cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and priuiledges belongyng to the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, what a cuſtome properly is.</note>And it is to bee ſpecially noted, there can be no cuſtome, vnleſſe it haue been vſed, time out of memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of man: and all ſuche cuſtomes as hee of that continuaunce, bee lawfull, ſo long as thei be not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, nor haue any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience that bee againſt reaſon. And note alſo, that no man can at this daie make, or bryng vp any newe cuſtome, but the ſame muſte be of auncient tyme but of mynde of man vſed, as is aforeſaid, or els
<pb facs="tcp:7121:24"/>t is no cuſtome.</p>
                  <p>And for as muche, as the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie cuſtomes of all Mannours, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not bée recited, yet for enſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake (emongeſt many) I will now note a fewe, moſte common.</p>
                  <p>Some Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour hath a cuſtome, that ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour can not be made of Landes holden of that Mannour, but to the Stewarde hymſelf: and yet in ſome Mannours it maie be doen to twoo of the Tenauntes, or Homage of that Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour. And in ſome Mannour, he Surrendour muſte bee made by the circumſtaunce of deliueryng a rod, ſtrawe, or mote, els is it a voide ſurrendour and in ſome Mannours it maie bee doen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
                  <p>Alſo in ſome Mannours the Tenauuntes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not leaſe, or ſet their landes aboue a yere, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the lordes licence, vpon paine of forfeiture of the ſame. And in ſome Mannours, for three yeres or more.</p>
                  <p>Inſome Mannours, the Tenauntes maie not fell, ne loppe, the woodes growyng vppon their tenementes, no, not to repaire their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, without the lordes licence: and yet in ſome Mannours, thei maie doe bothe, yea, and ſell the woode awaie, without the Lordes licence.</p>
                  <p>In ſome Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nours, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhire, Somerſetſhire, Dorſetſhire, Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Witſhire, and part of Gloceſterſhire, the Tenauntes take the cuſtomarie Landes of the Lorde, for tearme of three liues, and not aboue, paiyng a fine vncertaine, as the Lorde and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte
<pb facs="tcp:7121:24"/>can agree. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in ſuche Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the wiues of the Tenauntes, after their houſebandes deceaſſes, haue their widowes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, by their cuſtome, which is as long as thei kepe theim ſelues vnmaried, and honeſte, and in ſome Mannours it is otherwiſe and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo in theſe Mannours, the lorde hath a her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riotte, after the death of euery Tenaunte.</p>
                  <p>In ſome Mannours, the Tenauntes haue their tenementes, to them and to their heires, paieyng to the Lorde a fine certaine, at euery chaunge, and there onely the wife, hath no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes eſtate, and alſo commonly ſuche Tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes paie Herriottes.</p>
                  <p>In ſome Mannours, the Tenauntes are bounde by their cuſtome, to ſerue the Lorde in the Quenes warres, ſo it be within the realme, againſt Rebels, or ſuche enemies, at their own proper coſtes and charges: And in ſome Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours it is otherwiſe: But note, that now by a ſtatute therefore made, all cuſtomarie tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes muſt ſerue their Lordes againſt Rebelles, vpon paine of forfeiture of their holdynges.</p>
                  <p>Alſo in ſome Mannours, the tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ought by their cuſtome, for three or fower daies in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng tyme, and aſmuche in mowyng tyme, and likewiſe in Harueſt, to helpe to tille the Lordes grounde, to make his Haye, or to helpe in with his Harueſte, whiche bee called commonlie <hi>opera cuſtumaria,</hi> that is to ſaie, daie woorkes, and ſuche like, and in ſome place thei vſe to doe it, onely with their perſones, and in ſome Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours bothe with their Teames, Waines, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, and perſones, and in ſome place other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:25"/>Alſo in ſome Mannours, the Tenauntes by their cuſtome, muſte grinde their Corne at no Mill, but at the lordes mille, belongyng to the Mannour, and this is commonly called So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as is aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>In ſome Mannours, the Tenauntes haue their Fewell out of the Lordes wooddes, and this in moſte places is properly called eſtouer, and in ſome Manours but onely timber, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairyng their tenauntries.</p>
                  <p>In ſome Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nours, their cuſtome is to haue common for their beaſtes, in all the lordes waſt grounde, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons. And in ſome Mannours but in a parte of theim, and that onely for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, and ſome ſpeciall kinde of cattaile, yea, and alſo in ſome places, at certaine tymes onely accuſtomed, or prefixed.</p>
                  <p>And as touchyng the deſcription, of the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie kindes of Common, that is to ſaie, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon appendaunte, Common appurtenaunte, Common engroſſe. &amp;c. I leaue thre to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of maſter Littleton,</p>
                  <p>And note for a ſpeciall Rule: a tenaunte that hath Common in the Lordes Commons, maie haue there nothyng by reaſon of Common, but alonely bitte of mouthe with their cattaile, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maie Geeſe or Swine haue common, but by the lordes ſufferaunce, without ſpeciall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the charter, or copie of the Tenaunt.</p>
                  <p>Sometyme cuſtomarie Tenauntes in ſome Mannours, haue alſo common of Fiſhing, with ſhouenettes, caſtyng neetes, ſmall pitches, and trodde nettes, and ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:25"/>Some Countries haue cuſtomes by theim ſelues, as the cuſtome of Gauell kinde in Rent, and parte of Wales, where the ſonnes of Free holders, ſhall haue their fathers landes equally deuided emongeſt theim, touchyng the whiche and all ſuche like cuſtomes, I committe you to the inſtruction of the learned in the lawe.</p>
                  <p>Priuiledges, are all ſuche liberties and frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſies, as are graunted to a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour, or toune by the Kyng Quene, or Princes greate Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, or letters patentes, or by acte of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption what repriſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly are.</note>Alſo there are commonlie goyng yerely out of moſte Mannours ſondrie Deductions, Paimentes, and dueties, and theſe are alwaies called Repriſes. And of ſuche there bee diuers natures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome goe out of one Mannour and ſome out of an other, as bee theſe enſuyng, and their like.</p>
                  <p>Suites of Courte, or annuall fine, for ſuite and ſeruice of Courte, to any other Courte.</p>
                  <p>Rent charge, or rent ſecke, yerely goyng out of any Mannour.</p>
                  <p>Sometymes alſo Rente ſeruice, either of Capons, Hennes, Peper, Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minſéede, or ſuche like, maye be yerely paied, out of one Mannour to an other.</p>
                  <p>And alſo a Rente, or a Suite, maie bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes paied out of a Mannour to a Hundred, or Sheriues Tourne.</p>
                  <p>Alſo an annuall pencion or porcion maie bee
<pb facs="tcp:7121:26"/>paied out of ſome one Mannour, to ſome other Mannour, Perſonage, or Vicuarage.</p>
                  <p>Item a Rente reſolute, maie ſometymes bee yerely goyng out of one Mannour, to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mannour or Parſonage, for a high waie, or a Water, courſe, or a libertie of foldyng, or ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>Alſo out of ſome Mannours or Landes, an yerely tenth is reſerued, to the Kyng or Quée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes highnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Repriſes of al natures.</note>Alſo yerely Fées to any Receiuour, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life, Collectour, high Stewarde, or vnder Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, charged by the Lordes Letters Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or otherwiſe, to bee goyng out of a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or ſuche Landes, are called Repriſes.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe euerie other yerely Fee, that is paied to anye other parſon, out of any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Landes or Tenementes.</p>
                  <p>Corrodies alſo for Tearme of life, or in Fée to any Parſone or Perſones, yerely paied out of any Mannour.</p>
                  <p>Stipendes, Salaries, or Annuities of Chapleynes, men of Counſell in the Lawe or ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorandum,</hi> all theſe Repriſes, aforeſaied, and their like, are to bee diligently learned, that thei maie be deducted, when thei ought out of any Mannour, in the makyng of the valewe thereof.</p>
                  <p>And when theſe ſixe principall thinges before in the ſaied ſeconde rule ſet out and deſcribed, are perfectly knowen, and well vnderſtanded of him that would bee a Surueiour, then hath he ſome entraunce in the knowledge of his Office. And
<pb facs="tcp:7121:26"/>
now here next enſuing, for his further enſtruction, ſhall enſue the thirde Rule, whiche ſhall containe in a brief rehearſall the ſumme of all ſuche partes and duties which doth or ought to belong to the Office of a Surueiour, and whiche then (after followyng in order) the ſpecialleſt pointes of them are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerlie by them ſelues, more at large to be touched and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="rule">
               <head>¶The thirde Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Breef Recitall of moſte of the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, dueties, and ſpeciall thynges, what, or whiche are belongyng ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to bee doen, and obſerued of euerie Surueiour, as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; partes, wherin generally the Office con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, and therefore here ſett together, that thei might the better be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in memorie, moſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be hereafter more at large diſcourſed &amp; ſet out.</p>
               <p>Alſo euery Surueiour ought to be as ſkilfull, and well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed how to make and certifie to the Lorde, the true and iuſt value of his Lordeſhippe, Mannour, Landes, Tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c. or any parte, parcell, or member thereof, when he ſhall be thereunto required and commaunded, and to make and ſet out the ſame in a plaine and breife particuler, whether it bee for the purpoſe or intente that the Lorde would ſell or leaſſe out any ſuche Mannour, or any parcell thereof to any parſon or parſones, as an Auditour. And truelie it were much to the Surueiours ſhame and reproche, if he cannot make as true and perfect a particuler thereof to the Lorde, when occaſion requireth (Surueiyng the ſame, once or twiſe in euerie yere as he ought to dooe) aſwell as the Auditour thereof, who maketh commonlie his Particuler of a Suruey taken per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce
<pb facs="tcp:7121:27"/>
ten or fiftene yeres before or ſuch like, or perchaunce but onely by his bare recorde of Miniſters accoumpte, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuruey. And ſurely, in this caſe the Auditour (who in déede is a verie néedefull and profitable member of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth) is worthie muche more commendation (that he is ready and can make a particuler by his Preſident or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters accoumpt, or ſuch like record,) then ſome Surueiour who neither can, nor hath learned how to doe it at all.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Surueiour ought to knowe how to take the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey and perfect vewe of a Mannour, or other Landes or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, and how to butte and bounde the ſame in due order, and for moſte plaineſt knowledge of the Tenauntes, and for moſte long continuaunce, an example whereof you ſhall haue hereafter.</p>
               <p>Then alſo how (when he hath ſurueied a Mannour) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and engroſſe the ſame, whiche he ought to doe, and alſo to make a terrour of the ſame, in due fourme as hereafter ſhall be declared.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the Surueiour ſhould kéepe a ſuite rolle, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all ſuche perſons as ought to yelde ſuite of Courte, of the Mannour or ſeruice ſhould bee written, and a Copie thereof he ſhould deliuer to the Stewarde, that they maie bee called at euerie Courte, or Lete holden, that the Lorde looſe none of his ſuites or ſeruices, a fourme whereof alſo enſueth.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, it is the Surueiours duetie, to make and keepe a Rolle or booke, called a cuſtomary of the Mannour, wherin all the cuſtomes of the Mannour ſhould bee regiſtred. That the Tenauntes maie at no time claime any more, or other cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes then they ought to haue, ne the Lorde bee preiudiced by any newe cuſtome, by his Tenauntes claimed. And this Cuſtomarie would bee Indented, the one parte to remaine with the Lorde or his Stewaade, and the other parte with his Tenauntes. And yet neuertheleſſe ſhould the Suruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours haue the originall Copie thereof, in the ende of the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:7121:27"/>
of the ſame Mannour, a brief forme whereof alſo you ſhall haue hereafter.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Surueiours ſhould geue to euery Bailife, Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, or Reue of euery mannour, a parfite rentall of the yere by Reuenues of the ſame Mannour, to gather it by, whiche rentall alſo ſhould be endented, the one parte to remaine with the Lorde or his Surueiour, and the other with the Bailife. A ſhorte example whereof ye ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Surueiour ſhould haue and kepe the Inrollment of all Indentures and Copies, by which any tenaunt holdeth that he may ſee the Lordes duelie aunſwered, of his Rentes, Duties and couenauntes in their writinges contained, and alſo be aſcertainee, of their Eſtates and grauntes to them by the Lorde made. And let the Surueiour that hath to doe in the weſt parties, looke diligently to this one pointe, that the name of a yong Infaunte crepe not into the place of an olde man, for they vſe muche there (I will not ſaie for that intent) if the Father or Mother who haue ſtate for life, in poſſeſſion or reuerſion, bee named Ihon and Agnes, or ſuche like, then if they haue ij or thrée boyes, or as many girles, their names ſhalbe all chriſtened as they or thoſe, who haue ſtate in their holdinges are named. But now this is more narowly looked to, then in tymes paſt.</p>
               <p>Alſo although euerie Steward is bound by lawe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to be an indifferent iudge, betwene the Lorde and his Tenauntes, and alſo to geue at the Court a true, full and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall Charge to the Homage, and alſo to make a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, aſwell of euery Tenauntes particuler eſtates, as of all other thinges in his Court Rolles, and to ſee the Tenaunts Copies truely made out accordingly: Yet becauſe it is the duetie of a Surueiour, to haue ſuche ſkill in the thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed, that hee may not onely keepe a note of all the ſtewardes doynges, but alſo be able to enforme, or peruſe the doinges of hym, I haue alſo hereafter therefore ſet breifly
<pb facs="tcp:7121:28"/>
out (the charge which a Stewarde ought to giue in a Court Baron) and alſo the forme of makyng out their Copies, as hereafter doth appeare,</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the Surueiour ought to haue ſome ſight, or knowledge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common lawe, or els he ſhall many tymes, by his ignoraunce, deceaue both the Tenaunt, and the Lorde, and alſo make euill Preſidentes and Recordes, and thereby muche trouble and inconuenience maie ariſe and growe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a daie hereafter, to the perill of his owne ſoule and many others.</p>
               <p>Alſo he ought to grow ripe and perfect, in the Lordes eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, and recordes of euery Mannour, and in the ordering and ſorting of them, that he maie bee able to aunſwere or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Lorde of the Mannour, or his counſaill, when anie title or clayme is made or other doubte put, and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Court Rolles woulde bee kept in Cheſtes made for that purpoſe, within any Mannor vnder lockes &amp; keies. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Alſo by the erection of the late Courte of Augmentation, and reuenue of the Kinges Crowne lately in the firſt yere of Quéene Marie, diſſolued, and reduced in the Exchequour, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other things (there appointed to the office and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a Surueiour) it was thought méete, that the Surueior ſitting with the Stewarde, after thrée Proclamations made in the Courte, ſhould aſſeſſe Fynes, make grauntes of Copie hold, and cuſtomarie Landes, being within the limites of his Office, according to the cuſtome of the Mannours, thereto ſuch parſon or parſons, as ſhould giue beſt Fine for the ſame, which the Stewarde then furthwith in open court, ought to chardge, and enter into the Court Rolle. And therof to make out the extractes to the Bailife, Reue or Collectour, that the ſame might be iuſtely leuied, and gathered accordingly. And alſo that the Surueiour ſhould ſée truely aunſwered, all ſuch Rentes, Reuenues, perquiſites, caſualties, and other things whiche maye growe profitable or beneficiall to the Lorde at
<pb facs="tcp:7121:28"/>
the next audite, for which purpoſe the Surueiour muſt kéepe a booke of all ſuche grauntes, to the intent that the ſame ſhall and may be the more truely aunſwered at the ſaid accoumpt: for els may happe the Steward either for lucre, or for negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of hym ſelfe or his Clerke, may conceale, or omit ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, to the deceipte aſwell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord as of his Tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Surueyour ſhould be partly ſkilled, in the rule of Apportionation, that he may when néede is, apportionate the Lande with the Rente, accordyng to the Acre, a ſhorte forme whereof ſhall bee hereafter declared, but this rule is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vncertaine.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Surueiour ſhould haue ſome ſkill in meaſuryng of Lande, that is to ſaie, what an Acre is, how muche it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, &amp;c. and how moſte readily, and truely to meate lande by line, or by rodde, be it in the plaine, in the valley, or vppon the hille, or in woodde, or bee it ſquare, triangle, rounde, or of any other proportion: A ſmall brief enſtruction, he ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after finde, ſet out with a readie table, for the contentes of all maner of lande.</p>
               <p>And now, as touchyng the maner and forme, how a true breef, and perfecte particular of any Mannour, Landes, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, or Hereditamentes, ſhould be made, and what thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be obſerued therein, I haue now (vnder correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) here vnder ſhewed you.</p>
               <p n="1">1 You muſte ſpecially note, that your particuler ought, ſhould, and muſt conſiſte in three principall poinctes, or nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thynges. The firſte is, that the true value of all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles of Landes, Tenementes, and Hereditamentes, be ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally (but breefly) deſcribed, and ſette out with their ſeuerall ſommes at the ende of them, and then all in the lefte margent (all ioyned in one line) the totall to be ſet out.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond is, that there vnder muſt, immediatly, plainly, and breefly be deſcribed, and ſet out, all the repriſes, that is to ſaie (as I haue before declared) all deductions, fees, or paie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:29"/>
goyng out of the ſaied value, to any perſone, or perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the ſummes at the ende: And then altogether in the lefte margente, to be in a line ioyned, and the totall to bee ſet out, as before in the value.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdlie, vnder theim bothe ſhould bee ſette forthe, the <hi>Remanet clare,</hi> written in Texte, and drawen out a long, with the ſumme in the ende of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Vnder all whiche, if there be any other thyng, needefull to bee conſidered, or remembred for the Lordes aduauntage, or otherwiſe: either touchyng the ſale, or leaſſyng of the ſaied Mannour, Landes, &amp;c. to any perſone, and whiche is not in the value mentioned: then the ſame ſhall be written vnder the particuler, in the title of a <hi>Memorandum. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow foraſmuche, as nothyng can bee by any meane ſo well vnderſtanded, as by waie of example, when it is ſet before the eye: Therefore I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a very ample particuler here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after enſuyng, and hereunto annexed. Wherein I haue fained, or ſuppoſed a Lordſhippe or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by the name of the Mannour of Dale, to haue all maner of Rentes, and other thynges, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaied, and in my ſeconde Rule ſpecified, or ſuche like, as commonly to any maner of Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, Mannour, Landes, or Tenementes, can or doeth belong: and there out I haue deducted in repriſes, all maner of deductions, or paimentes, that can, or doeth commonly, yerely, go out, or be deducted out of any Lordſhip, or Mannour, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp;c. with the <hi>Reamne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t clare</hi> there after folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and a memor <abbr>and</abbr> there vnder, as amply as I can preſently alſo gather, that to ſuche, a value ſhould, or maie appertaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="rule">
               <pb facs="tcp:7121:29"/>
               <head>¶The Fourth Rule. <hi>How a Surueiour ſhould take a</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ievv or Suruey of a Mannour or ſuch Landes Tenementes or Hereditamentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt the Surueiour in takyng his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey, ſhould well remember that he ought, moſte diligently and vigilauntly to vewe and ſuruey the Buttes, and Boundes of the whole Mannour, and then the Buttes and Boundes, of euery perticuler Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts landes, Tenements, Meadowes, Cloaſes, Paſtures, &amp;c. within the ſame Mannour, and euery parcell thereof, that it may remaine in perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce hereafter, what and whiche Tenementes, Landes, Meadowes, Paſtures, &amp;c. euery man had, when the Suruey was taken, and where the ſame then did lie, and howe they were then bounded and butted, and vpon whom, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Acres, euery parcell did containe, and how muche lande or paſture did at the ſame tyme belong to euery Tenauntes hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, or to the Mannour houſe: aſwell for the preſeruation of the inheritaunce of the Lorde of the Mannour, as of euery freeholder, Copy holder or cuſtomary holder, or other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of the ſame.</p>
               <p>The whiche Surueiour when he goeth about to vewe or ſuruey a Mannour, Landes, Tenementes or other Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, ſhould haue with hym redy prouided a Paperbooke, wherein he may roughly and ſpéedily note as he goeth about the vewe thereof, the firſt drought of his Suruey of the ſame, leſte if it be doone in looſe papers, ſome parte may happen to be loſſe, or els vnſorted or alter miſplaced in the ingroſſyng, and ſo perchaunce, as good neuer written. And in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:7121:30"/>
of the ſame paper booke, let hym write the title in this fourme, if he pleaſe, writing the Mannours name in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent on this wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium de Sale.</note>
                  <abbr>Superuil.</abbr> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Sale ibidem cape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>fact</abbr> et <abbr>examinat</abbr> per <abbr>diligent</abbr>, et exact viſ. perambulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, examinationem et menſuratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tam A. B. <abbr>general</abbr> ſuperuiſor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at Stile, dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> et per <abbr>mandat</abbr> eiuſdem, quam per <abbr>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</abbr> R. S. F. H. T. B. ac multorum tenentium, et Homagij Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr>, tunc ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exiſten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xij. die Auguſti. Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i M. D. lxij. Annoque Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Elizabeth Dei gratia Anglie, &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
               <p>Or rather if ye will, you may in your firſt waſt paper boke, (ſo it be not in Engliſh in your engroſſed booke of Suruey) write the title in Engliſhe in a ſhorter fourme, which is this enſuyng both will ſerue.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>¶The Toune of Dale.</hi> The vewe of the Mannour of Dale, taken the x. day of May in the xiiii. yere of the raigne of King Henry the eight. By A. B. generall Surueiour to the right honourable lorde. C. D. Lorde of the ſame by his Commaundement, and alſo by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of E. F. &amp; G. H. and many other tenauntes of the ſame, as hereafter enſueth.</head>
                  <p>Then in myne opinion, (vnder correction) the Surueiour ſhould firſt beginne with the Scite of the Mannour or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Mannour place, if there be any, and firſte to ſet out the boundes thereof by euery ſide, that is to ſaie by Eaſt, Weaſt, North and South. And then the contentes what it contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:7121:30"/>
in length and breadth. Thou what edifices, buildinges, and houſes of offices Barnes, Stables, Stalles, and Doue-houſes are ſtandyng vpon the ſame, and whether builded with Tymber, Bricke, or Freeſtone, Tyled, ſtated, ſhingled, or thatched. And what Gardens, Orchardes, Motes, or Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, be about the ſame, or adioynyng thereto. And then if ye will (though maiſter Fitz Harbert, haue not altogether ſo ſet foorth) he may goe ſtraight to the ſurueiyng of the Demai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that is, what ſeuerall, or particuler Cloſes, Meadowes, Paſtures, arable lande, &amp;c. they are of, which be the Demai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And where they doe lie, and if they haue any proper or peculiar names, then what euery parcell of ground is called, and how many Acres euery parcell doth containe, and howe they butte and bounde. And what woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des bee thereof, and how many yeres grouth: alſo what Shawes, or good hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of wood be about euery fence, of any Cloſe of the ſaid Demaines. And then if a Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>our holdeth it, what is his name, and what yerely rent he paieth, and at what feaſtes the ſome is paiable, and alſo the date of the Farmours Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Leaſſe (if he haue any) and for what tearme of yeres or liues he holdeth it, and vnder what couenauntes, as by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample hereafter.</p>
                  <p>Then in like maner of the Scite of the Parſonage (if there be any) Buttyng, boundyng, containyng and recityng, the ſame in all pointes as is before expreſſed in the Scyte of the Mannour. Adding who is Perſon, or Vicar there, to whom the gifte thereof belongeth, who occupieth it, and what it is yerely worth. And alſo likewiſe namyng, buttyng, bounding, and ſhewing the contentes and names of euery parcell of the glebe landes, thereto belongyng accordingly.</p>
                  <p>Then to take the viewe of Tenementes, of Freeholders, and of their Landes, Meadowes and Paſtures, &amp;c. Alwaies buttyng, boundyng, containyng, and recityng the contentes and proper names of euery parcell thereof, accordyng as is
<pb facs="tcp:7121:31"/>
aforeſaide. And ſpecially remembryng by what rent, ſeruice, reliefe, Fyne, Herriot, Suite of Court, or cuſtumary workes, they doe holde the ſame of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>And in like maner to vewe the Tenementes and Landes of all manner of Tennauntes at wille, Tennauntes by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, or by Copie, &amp;c. Alwaies buttyng, boundyng, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, recityng, notyng and declaryng the ſeuerall contentes and names of euery particuler parcell of Lande, Meadowe, Paſture, Cloſe, Crofte, Wood, Shawe, &amp;c. And alſo the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall yerely Rentes, ſuites, ſeruices and workes, and the Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Heriottes, and cuſtomes, of the ſame. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And it were good, that ye vewed the Fieldes, in a generall maner, euery fielde ſeuerally by hym ſelf. Hauyng if ye be not the ſkilfuller, a Diall in your hande (accordyng to maiſter Fitz herbertes counſaile) I meane that thereby, who ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſuruey, may thereby know perfectly, which is Eaſte, Weſte, North and South. And the Surueiour ſhould ſtande in the middes of the fielde, or where he may beſt ſee euery ſide or corner thereof. And as touchyng the buttyng and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the fieldes, before he doe begynne to enter the buttes and boundes of any particuler mans grounde, or lande in the ſame fielde, he ſhould enter the buttyng, and boundyng of the whole fieldes on euery ſide, how it doth lie, naming the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges thereof, alwaies vpon the moſt notable knowen mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or Meareſtones as he can: as theſe and ſuche like be that follow: Marelepittes, grauell pittes. Brokes, pondes, Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milles and Windmill hilles, croſſe waies, Lanes and ſuche like boundes, not remoueable and of continuaunce. And after he hath ſo butted and bounded the whole fielde, on all partes, Then to beginne at one place certaine, and ſo from thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to bound &amp; butte euery tenaunts particular furlonges, Landes, Hedlandes, Bawkes and groundes, be it by the lande or by the Acre, as he ſhall thinke beſt, or deuiſe to do the ſame, for ſurer, longer, and mens better knowledge thereof, as in
<pb facs="tcp:7121:31"/>
example hereafter ſhal appeare. Maiſter Fitzherbert would haue the Meadowes, paſtures and Cloſes alſo likewiſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied generally.</p>
                  <p>And the like maner &amp; forme in all pointes, is to be vſed by the Surueiour, in buttyng, and boundyng of the Meadowes that bee common Meadowes, with their ſeuerall contentes of Acres, by their ſeuerall markes, and Meareſtones, as exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſhewe alſo hereafter.</p>
                  <p>And as for Cloſes, Croftes, Paſtures, or Woodes that bee encloſed, he ſhould butte and bounde them ſeuerallie, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryng their contentes of Acres, and names if he can, with the value what thei bée yerely worthe, and who holdeth them, as is afore ſaied, whereof ye ſhall alſo haue an example here followyng in his place.</p>
                  <p>And after like maner and forme, maie the Surueiour, if he will, butte, bounde, and enter the contentes of Acres, of all maner of Paſtures, where Herdmen keepe cattalle. And alſo all Commons, Moores, Marſhes, Heathes, Common Woodes, or ſuche like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hereafter doe followe the examples, how the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes ſhould be entred orderly. And firſt how the Mannour place, or Scite ſhould bée entred, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bounded.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Citus Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr> Scituatur, et exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit, inter Cemiterium Eccleſie de Dale, ſuper le <abbr>Borial</abbr>, et Regiam viam di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſt, a villa de B. vſque villam de A. ſuper <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> et communem campum eiuſdem ville, ſuper Orient, et Tentm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue Meſuagium R. F. ſuper <abbr>occident</abbr>. Et continet in latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine triginta perticas, et quatuor pedes terre, vnaqueque pertica exiſten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xvi. pedes di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Super quem Scitum le Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:7121:32"/>
place <abbr>ſcituat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>ſufficient</abbr> 
                     <abbr>edificat</abbr> cum vna Aula, &amp; duabus cameris, ex lapidibus <abbr>quadrat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>conſtruct</abbr>, cum omnibus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, edificiis, cameris, ſtructur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et duobus atriis eidem Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Necnon vnum Columbarium, in exteriori A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> le greate Courte, <abbr>ſcituat</abbr>, cum vno Gardino <abbr>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>murat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>cont</abbr> vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ac vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hortu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</abbr> quatuor Acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnde vnum caput abbuttat ſuper Regiam viam predictam, verfue <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et ſuper ſcitum <abbr>pred</abbr> verſus <abbr>occident</abbr>, et ſuper campu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> verſus Auſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et clm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rectoris ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuper <abbr>Orient</abbr>, Ac etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum duobus Horreis, <abbr>continent</abbr> quatuor Bayes, le peece, vna domo <abbr>vocat</abbr> le Stalle, <abbr>als</abbr> le Oxe houſe, continen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iii. Baies, <abbr>edificat</abbr>, vnum <abbr>Srabul</abbr> 
                     <abbr>cont</abbr> vi. Baies, edific<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Qui quidem Scitus, et cetere damus, et edificia, ſunc <abbr>coopert</abbr>, cum tegu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſiue <abbr>lapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </abbr>, voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tyle, preter <abbr>dict</abbr> duo Horrea que <abbr>coopert</abbr> ſunt cum le Shingle &amp;c. Et qui quidem Scitus, &amp; cetere do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ac edificia, ac cetera premiſſ. cum omnibus et ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis dominicis terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>prat</abbr>, paſc. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, boſcis, et ſubboſcis, cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if it bee out of the Lordes owne hande, demiſed to a Fermour, ye muſt ſaie) modo dimittuntur, R. H. executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis, (Some vſe to ſpecifie the Farmours eſtate, with the date of his Indenture, and for what liues, or how many yeres he holdeth it) and this is more then is in Maſter Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harbertes preſidente (and then muſt ye ſaie) <abbr>Hend</abbr> et <abbr>Tenend</abbr> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> R.H. executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis a feſto ſancti Michaelis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeli prox. futur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (vel vlti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o preterito, as the feaſte is, and if it be for his life, ſaie) ad terminum et pro termino vite <abbr>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</abbr> ipſius R.H. (And if it bee for yeres, then ſaie) vſque ad finem et terminum xxj. annorum (or ſo many yeres as it is) extunc prox. <abbr>ſequend</abbr> et plenarie <abbr>complend</abbr>. And then name the rente, ſaiyng. <abbr>Reddend</abbr> inde annuatim <abbr>dict</abbr> Iohanni at Stile dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr> xxxi. <abbr>li.</abbr> x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. (or naming what other re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he paieth, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at what feaſtes as) ad duos a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni terminos vſuales, viz ad <abbr>feſt</abbr> Annunciationis beate Marie virginis, et ſancti Michaelis Archangeli, per <abbr>equal</abbr> portiones duran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino
<pb facs="tcp:7121:32"/>
                     <abbr>pred</abbr>. (And then ſome doe touche partly the couenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the Indenture, on the tenauntes behalfe to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in this or like forme.) Et <abbr>pred</abbr> R. H. et executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fui te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur omnibus reparationibus premiſſor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad ſumptos ſuos proprios preter grande meremium, et in fine termini dabit dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. nomine <abbr>Herriott</abbr>, et habebit ſufficien<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hedgebdote, Houſeboote, Fireboote, Ploughboote, Carteboote, et Haie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boote ſuper premiſſ. creſcen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>expendend</abbr>, et non alibi, duran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termino <abbr>pred</abbr>, et he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muniam in omnibus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis et vaſtis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i et <abbr>continet</abbr> etiam in Indentura <abbr>pred</abbr> vnum promſo; ꝙ ſi Reddu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <abbr>pred</abbr> aretrofuerit in parte vel in tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> per ſpatium vnius menſis poſt aliquod feſtum ſolutionis <abbr>pred</abbr>, et <abbr>litime</abbr> 
                     <abbr>demandat</abbr>, quod tunc poteſt dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s et heredes ſui in premiſſa, et quamlibet inde percellam reintrare &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And likewiſe you maie bréefly in the ſame maner, rehearſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther couenaunte in the Indenture declared) all whiche is more then maſter Fitz harbert declareth, and it is muche v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at this daie. And then ye muſte drawe all together, and ſet the rente thereof in the middeſt of the right margente, that it maie be ready to the eye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How the Sry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of a Perſonage or Rectorie, and Vicaredge may be bounded.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Citus Rectorie de Sale ſcituatur et exiſtit inter Regiam viam <abbr>pred</abbr> ſuper auſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et ecclia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m <abbr>ꝑochial</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr> et campum <abbr>Boreal</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et Tentm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> R.F. ex parte <abbr>oriental</abbr>. Et Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor eccleſie <abbr>pred</abbr> habet vnum Croftum <abbr>iacent</abbr> inter campum <abbr>Boreal</abbr> et Cemiteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſie <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>. Ac <abbr>dict</abbr> Croſtum continet detem perticas ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr> et duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decim perticas ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et Triginta perticas in longitudine ex <abbr>Oriental</abbr> parte, et viginti perticas et dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam ex parte <abbr>occidental</abbr>. Et R.T. eſt modo rector ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit
<pb facs="tcp:7121:33"/>
rectoriam <abbr>pred</abbr> ex dono domini huius Manerij de Dale, cui donatio eiuſdem pertinet imꝑꝑm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt vero et iudubitato patrono eiuſdem in iure Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui predicti. Et <abbr>predit</abbr>. R. T. cli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cus tenet rectoriam <abbr>pred</abbr>, cum omnibus Terris, Glebis, Pratis, Paſcuis, paſturis, decim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, oblacoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan>, prouencoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan>; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueucoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; alijs proficuis quibuſcunque in occupatione ſua propria, et valor annuus eiuſdem in libris Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Regine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit ad x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iij. l. ij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <abbr>ſed</abbr> valet per annum vltra repris<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xxij. l.</p>
                  <p>And note that the cauſe why I haue neither in the Scite and Demaynes of the Mannour afore mencioned, nor in the entrie of the ſaide Scite of the Perſonage aforeſaide, here butted, bounded or ſet out the names, contentes of Acres of the ſaid Landes, Meadowes, Paſtures, Cloſes, &amp;c. of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines or Glebe Landes, or of the Landes, Meadowes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. &amp;c. belonging to any tenement of frée holders, or copy holders, (the fourmes of thentries whereof nowe alſo enſue) is, becauſe the ſame muſt and ſhould appeare in the generall vewes of the fieldes, Meadowes and cloſes of the hole Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by them ſelues as hereafter ſhall appeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How the Tenementes or Meſuages of Fréehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhould be butted, bounded and entred.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Num Meſuagium ſiue tenementum, quod D. C. tenet libere per chartam cum omnibus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, prat, paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. eidem tenemento ſiue Meſſ. ꝑtin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o huius Manerij: quod quidem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuagium ſiue Tenementum iacet inter regiam viam <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et campum <abbr>Borial</abbr> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Borial</abbr>, et rectoriam <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et Ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> W. R. ex parte <abbr>Oriental</abbr>, et continet xiii. perticas ex parte <abbr>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtral</abbr> eiuſdem in latitudine et xxi. perticas et tres pedes in longitudine, et xvi. perticas in latitudine apud caput <abbr>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reol</abbr>.
<pb facs="tcp:7121:33"/>
Et tenet Meſuagium ſiue Tenementum predict cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o domino per homagium, fidelitatem et duos <abbr>ſolidat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>reddit</abbr> per annum, et vnam libram Piperis, ac <abbr>ſect</abbr> ad curiam dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i de tri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan> ſepti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>anis in tres ſepti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>anas, et ad duas letas dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> annuatim <abbr>tenend</abbr>.</p>
                  <p>And thus muſt ye enter the Meſuages, Landes and paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of all free holders beyng alwaies ſure to expreſſe the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; boundes of the ſame, and the ſeruice and yerely Rent of euery free Tenaunt as nere as ye can, in the entrie of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How other Meſuages, Tenementes or Cotages, holden of the Lorde at wille, or by Indenture, or by Copy of Courte rolle, ſhould be butted, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, contained and entred.</head>
                  <p>VNum Meſuagium ſiue Tenementum dimiſſum. S.H. (if it be at wille, ſay, ad voluntatem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i (if it be by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture, ſay) per Indenturam <abbr>gerent</abbr> 
                     <abbr>dat</abbr>, &amp;c. (if it bee by Copie of Court roll) ſaye, per copiam Curie ad volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, ſecundum conſuetudinem Manerij, cuius <abbr>dat</abbr> eſt, &amp;c. <abbr>Scituat</abbr> inter regiam viam <abbr>predict</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum Borealem <abbr>predict</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et dictum <abbr>Tenement</abbr> D.C. <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em Campum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat</abbr> Le Eſt fielde ex parte <abbr>Oriental</abbr>, et continet in latitudine quatuordecem pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et tres pedes aſſiſe, et xviii pertit<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem pedes aſſis<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in longitudine, he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd &amp;c. (as his eſtate is, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng the fourme ſet out in the entrie of the Scyte of the Mannour before expreſſed.) <abbr>Reddend</abbr> inde annuatim <abbr>dict</abbr> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anni Style dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>predict</abbr> xxiiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. ad duos a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos <abbr>vſual</abbr>, vz. ad feſta Annuntiationis beate Marie virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, et ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Michaelis Archangeli per equales porcoe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. (And then if it be by Indenture, touche alſo the couenauntes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in this or like fourme.) Et <abbr>pred.</abbr> S. H. et executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui per
<pb facs="tcp:7121:34"/>
Indentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> tenentur omnibus reparationibus premiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ad ſumptus ſuos proprios (grandi maremio ſolummodo <abbr>ercept</abbr>) Et in fine termini ſui dabit domino optimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Animal quod he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nomine <abbr>Herriott</abbr>. Et <abbr>pred</abbr> S. H. et <abbr>execut</abbr> ſui habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt (ex conuentione dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i predicti,) <abbr>Sufficient</abbr> hedgeboote, houſeboote, fyreboote, Ploughboote et Carteboote, ſuper p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſ. creſcen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expendend. duran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termino predicto. Et faciet Sectam ad curia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini quotie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s legaliter ſummoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus fuerit. Et dabit annuatim dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o <abbr>predco</abbr>, duas gallinas ad <abbr>Feſt</abbr> 
                     <abbr>natal</abbr> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, &amp;c. Et ſi reddu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <abbr>predict</abbr> aretro fuerit in parte vel in toto per ſpacium vnius menſis poſt aliquod feſtum ſolucon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> et liti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me <abbr>demandat</abbr>, quod tunc poteſt dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s et heredes ſui in p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſ. reintrar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. (And euen in like fourme let hym enter al other couenauntes contained in the Indenture.) And if it be by Copy ye muſte recite the ſeruices and woorkes whiche the Tenaunt ſhould doe if hee ſhould or ought to doe any, &amp;c. and in this fourme make your entrie of all ſuche like.</p>
                  <p>Now touchyng the entrie of the Fieldes, Landes, Cloſes and meadowes of euery Tenement (after Maiſter Fitzhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartes fourme) they muſt be recited in the vewe of the whole mannour, as next hereafter enſuyng ſhall appeare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Howe to Butte and Bounde the whole common fieldes belonging to a Mannour.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ampus <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacet ex auſtrali parte vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le de Sale <abbr>pred</abbr>, et incipit apud le Crucem ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Shawcroſſe, apud quoddam furlongu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat</abbr> Well Furlong. Quod quidem Furlongum continet ſexaginta acras terre <abbr>arabil</abbr> et abbut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ex parte <abbr>boreal</abbr> 
                     <abbr>et</abbr> 
                     <abbr>occidental</abbr>, ſuper magnum Clauſum dm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de terris dominicis voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrangcloſe, et ex parte <abbr>oriental</abbr> ſuper communem viam ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longlane, et ex parte <abbr>auſtral</abbr>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:34"/>
ſuper Riuulum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vocatur Kernebroke, vnde Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s habet tres acras et vnam rodam, rector ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et iiii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. R. F. quatuor acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. G.H. vnam acram et vnam rodam, S. R. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptem acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et tres <abbr>rod.</abbr> et ſic de ceteris. Ye may doe the like if ye will by the Landes as I haue doen by the acres.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if there bee any mo common Fieldes, enter them and bounde them in like maner, as I haue doen this South fielde aforemencioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to but and bound the Meadowes of a Man, nour, and ſpecially when they are common Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commune Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Sale <abbr>predict</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Brodemeade, iacet in <abbr>Orientali</abbr> campo coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Southfield, inter campum <abbr>pred</abbr> et Riuulum <abbr>predict</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Kernebrooke, et ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te <abbr>Occidental</abbr> abbuttat ſuper viam <abbr>vocat</abbr> long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane <abbr>pred</abbr>, et ex partibus <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> et <abbr>Oriental</abbr> 
                     <abbr>abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</abbr> ſuper clauſ. dedn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i <abbr>vocat</abbr> Wrangcloſe, et ex parte <abbr>Borcal</abbr> 
                     <abbr>abbut</abbr> ſuper Crofta I. H. et W. H. Et Pratum predictum continet lxiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vnam rodam, et iacet in diuerſis partib. <abbr>vocat</abbr> Shootes. Et incipiens apud longlane <abbr>pred</abbr> in auſtrali parte eiuſdem, rector ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet tres Acras et vnam Rodam, dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt de dni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cis ſuis ſex Acras. R. S. v. acras et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I. B. quatuor acras et vnam rodam. F. H. ſex acras et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. T.B. v. acras, Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a Regina ix. acras, Rector <abbr>predict</abbr> tres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. et ſic de ceteris his <abbr>Sili<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>bus</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </abbr>.</p>
                  <p>And if there bee any moe or other Meadowes, vſe the lyke fourme of entryng of their Buttes Boundes and contentes, notyng alwayes their knowen names ſpecially if you can.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How a man ſhould enter, butte and bound the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
<pb facs="tcp:7121:35"/>
Paſtures, Croftes and Encloſures belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng to a Manour.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nam Clauſur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quadraginta acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacet inter Pratum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Brodemeade ex parte <abbr>oriental</abbr>, et v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num clauſſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> R. F. <abbr>vocat</abbr> Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft, et Riuulum <abbr>predic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Kernebroke ex partibus <abbr>Occidental</abbr> et <abbr>auſtral</abbr>, ac co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em Campum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Northfield, ex parte Boriale, et valet per annum vi. l.</p>
                  <p>Vnum aliud clauſſ. Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod R.F. tenet libe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o <abbr>pred</abbr> vt libo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſuo ꝑtinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Welcrofte <abbr>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</abbr> xiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacet inter wrangcloſe predict. ſuper <abbr>Occidental</abbr> et clm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. S. T. <abbr>vocat</abbr> olde Acre, ex parte <abbr>Oriental</abbr> &amp; riuulum predict<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </abbr> Kernebrooke, ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et campum <abbr>predict</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Northefelde, et <abbr>val</abbr> per annum. xxx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d.</p>
                  <p>Vnum aliud clauſ. Paſture quod G. H. tenet de domino, vt Ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſuo cuſtumario pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>cont</abbr> xxiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et iii. Rodas <abbr>vocat</abbr> Marlefelde, iacet iuxta Wrangcloſe <abbr>pred</abbr>, <abbr>abbut</abbr> ſuper Longlane <abbr>pred</abbr> verſus <abbr>Oriental</abbr> et clm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I. M. <abbr>vocat</abbr> Short-acre, verſus <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et clm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rectoris eccleſie ibidem voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Parſones Cloſe ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et <abbr>dict</abbr> clm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Well crofte ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et valet per annum xxxii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Vnum Clauſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Parſones cloſe, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xxii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et vnam Rodam iacet ſuper clauſſ. <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Shortacre verſus <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et clauſ. <abbr>vocat</abbr> Welcrofte, verſus <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et Longlane verſus <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et clauſ. R.F. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <abbr>Oriental</abbr>, pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rectorie de Sale <abbr>pred</abbr>, <abbr>val</abbr> per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. xxvi. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. d.</p>
                  <p>And after this and like maner, ye maie peruſe, vewe, butte and bounde, and enter all maner of Cloſes, Paſtures and Croftes in any Mannour, or about any Mannour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:35"/>And you ſhall note, that this maner and forme of vewyng, buttyng, boundyng, and entryng of the ſaied Meſſuages, or Tenementes, Fieldes, Meadowes, and Paſtures, or Cloſes, is almoſte whollie accordyng to the forme, preſcribed by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Fitz Harbert, and is a very exacte and moſte perfect way.</p>
                  <p>But there is now vſed of ſome, an other maner of Suruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, Buttyng, and Boundyng, but ſpecially of entryng of the ſame in theſe latter daies, whereof I would not haue you alſo ignoraunte, &amp; that is in this forme: Thei entre ſeuerally euery mannes Meſſuage, or Tenement, and Butte and bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d firſt the Scite therof accordingly, and then euen in the ſame entre all in one (infra) thei doe particularly butte and bound, and alſo entre euery mannes errable lande, alſo his Meado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, Cloſes, and Paſtures, belongyng to euery of the ſame ſeuerall Tenementes, all together, and then ſee out the rente in the right margent thereof, and the fine and Herriot there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to bee due in the lefte margente thereof, as for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, I will ſett out hereafter onely one example.</p>
                  <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rnoldus at Noke tenet per In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>gerent</abbr> 
                     <abbr>dat</abbr> xii. die Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij, anno regni Regis Henr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viii. xxxiiii. dnum magn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum ſiue <abbr>capital</abbr> Meſſuagium ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Halle greene, <abbr>ſcitual</abbr> et exiſtens apud plateam ſiue vicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Strowde croſſe, inter v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam viam ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Strowdelane ex parte <abbr>Oriental</abbr> et coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Strowdegrene ex <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> et qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dam Croftam in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ap Moore, ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, &amp; cuiuſdam alii <abbr>croft</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Hall crofte, in tenura eiuſdam Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldi ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et continet in lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudine triginta octo perticas, et xi. pedes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:36"/>
et in latitudine viginti nouem pertit<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queque pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exiſtens xvi. pedes et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Super quam Scitum et <abbr>predict</abbr> capitale Meſſuagium ſcituatur ſufficienter <abbr>edificat</abbr> viz vna aula cum vna camera, et vna parua camera <abbr>vocat</abbr> a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ſuper Aulam <abbr>pred</abbr> ex <abbr>quadrat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>lapid</abbr> 
                     <abbr>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct</abbr> &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cum ceteris domibus et edificijs, et ſtructuc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eidem <abbr>annexat</abbr>, acetiam vnum atrium <abbr>quadrat</abbr> eidem aule adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, necnon vnum <note place="margin">xiiii. l. xiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicto atrio contingen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac etiam vnum gardinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vnum pomarium adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percat</abbr> ſiue <abbr>palat</abbr>, continen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in toto tres rodas, &amp; quatuor pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnde vnum caput pomarij <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ſuper Regiam viam <abbr>vocat</abbr> Strowde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane <abbr>pred</abbr> verſus Orien<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ſuꝑ le Grene <abbr>pred</abbr> &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ac etiam vnum pratum <abbr>vocat</abbr> Longe Meade, continen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xii. acres, quod quidem pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iacet in <abbr>Occidental</abbr> parte campi voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felde, et <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ſuper Riuulum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lowe-water ſuper <abbr>Orient</abbr> &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) and ſo namyng euery Cloſe, Meadowe, or parcell of lande arable, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertainyng to the ſame Tenemente, and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame on al ſides, as I haue before part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewe you, then ſaiyng) cum omnibus et ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis ſuis pertinentijs quibuſcunque, <abbr>hend</abbr> ſibi executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; aſſignatis ſuis a <abbr>feft</abbr> ſancti Michae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Archi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vltimo preterito ante <abbr>dat</abbr> Indenture <abbr>pred</abbr>, ad terminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viginti et vnius annorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunc proxime ſequen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et <abbr>complend</abbr>. <abbr>Reddend</abbr> inde annuatim dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Mauer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>hered</abbr> &amp; aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis xiiii. l. xiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. legalis monete Anglie, ad <abbr>feſt</abbr> 
                     <abbr>natal</abbr> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, et natiuitatis ſcti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioannis Baptiſte per <abbr>equal</abbr> portiones, vt per Iudentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <abbr>al</abbr> plenius apparet. &amp;c.</q>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:36"/>And this fourme aforeſaid ſemeth alſo very commodious, for it ſheweth together plainely to the eye, what, how, and where the parcells of landes be, that doth belong to euery te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement or meſuage, wheras after the fourme afore ſurueied, after ye haue founde in your ſuruey, a tenauntes meſuage or houſe, ye muſt be faine to ſéeke and pike out in the general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the whole ſuruey of Fieldes, Meadowes and Cloaſes of the ſame Mannour, euery tenauntes parcelles particuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Whiche is a trouble and ſomewhat diffuſe to hym that is but a young ſurueiour. Mary, to helpe that, it is vſed (after the ſuruey of a Mannour is generally taken in fourme afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: Then immediatly therout to make your Terrour wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery mans parcelles of Lande are ſet out with his tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, partely in fourme of the laſt example aforeſaide.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="rule">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶The fifte Rule.</hi> The deſcription and enſtruction for the makyng and engroſſyng of a Terrour, of a Mannour or ſuche landes, tenements and hereditamentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough ſome men make no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene a Suruey &amp; a Terror, accompting all to be one thing, yet truely as farre as I could euer learne and vnderſtand, there is muche difference. One difference is that before laſt remembred, that is to ſay, in the ingroſment thereof, to enter, and ſet out euery tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes parcelles of La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, Meadowes, paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and Cloſes (out of the generaltie of the Suruey) with their ſeuerall names, Buttes and Boundes all together ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with their tenement, all in one infra, as it were. Alſo in the terrour, ſome vſe firſt to beginne with the declaration, of the circuite, then of whom the Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nour landes &amp;c. is holden,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:37"/>
and by what ſeruice, as example here enſuyng declareth. Then the entry of the Scyte of the Mannour place with the Demaynes. Then the Parſonage or Vicaredge with the Glebe Landes, then the entries firſt of free holders, then of Tenauntes at will, if there be any: then of Tenauntes by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture for terme of life or yeres: then the entryng of the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes of the Copiholde or Cuſtumary Landes, and laſt of all, the entrie of the common Mores, Marſhes, Woddes and Eſtouers belonging to the ſame Mannour, with their boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and butmentes, as example of a briefe terrour ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after declare vnto you. Which I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie ſubmit vnto the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the learned. And ſome vſe in entring of their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, to ſet the names of euery Tenaunte with the fine and Herriotes (if they owe any) in the left margent, and the yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rent in the right margent.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Manerium de Dale in Comitatu praedicto.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Comitat</abbr> Northu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Agnum Terrarium Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at Stile mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis, dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr> de eodem Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio diligenter <abbr>renouat</abbr>, <abbr>fact</abbr>, et examinat per <abbr>Mandat</abbr> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i <abbr>predict</abbr>, vltimo die Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſti. Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i M.D.lxij. Annoque Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gni Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Noſtre Elizabeth Dei gratia Anglie Frauncie et Hibernie Regine fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei defenſor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>idelicet.</head>
                  <p>CIrcuitur Manerij de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>, incipit apud le croſſe Way <abbr>vocat</abbr> Shawe croſſe apud <abbr>Orient</abbr>, <abbr>ducent</abbr> ad Burgu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de B. et exterdit a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a via per ſepem mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ij, <abbr>vocat</abbr> le Hethe Downe, vſque ad locum quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam
<pb facs="tcp:7121:37"/>
                     <note place="margin">Circuitus Maner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d Dale, cun metis et boundis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſdem.</note>
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> le grauell pittes, in exteriore parte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ij <abbr>predict</abbr>, et abinde <abbr>extend</abbr> per magnum foſſ. <abbr>vocat</abbr> the drie diche, verſus Auſtrum, vſque par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum riuulum <abbr>vocat</abbr> Slades Brooke, et abinde extendens ſemper a longe per Riuulum <abbr>pred</abbr> verſus <abbr>occidental</abbr>, vſque ad <abbr>molend</abbr> pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manerio de H. <abbr>vocat</abbr> Huttes mylle, et abinde reextendit per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em viam ſine callem ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <abbr>boreal</abbr> vſque ad Stagnum quoddam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <abbr>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat</abbr> Helliers ponde, et abinde circumextendens per corneriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Parci Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr>, &amp; per ſepem <abbr>vocat</abbr> le greate quickſett camporum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manerij voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. G. adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſque ad le croſſe waie <abbr>vocat</abbr> Shawe croſſe <abbr>pred</abbr>.</p>
                  <p>Qui quidem notabiles ſiue <abbr>ſpecial</abbr> loci <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>at</abbr> Shawcroſſe, Grauell Pittes, Slades Brooke, Hittes mille, et Heliers ponde, ſunt et ſemper de antiquo fueri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t limites, ſeu le perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, markes, et meares totius <abbr>precint</abbr> ſiue circuitus Manerij de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Tenura, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue de quo <abbr>tenet</abbr> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerium de Dale et per que <abbr>redd</abbr> et <abbr>ſcruit</abbr>.</note>Manerium de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr> cum omnibus et ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis terris, tenementis, pratis, paſcuis, paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, et ceteris ſuis iuribus, membr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs tenetur de H. Comite Northumbrie, vt de vni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o ſiue manerio ſuo de C. per libm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Soccagiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et <abbr>reddit</abbr> xxxiiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ij. d. ob q. annuati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>ſolut</abbr> ad fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Michaelis Archangeli tantum.</p>
                  <q>Vel al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> li tenetur de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a Regina in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite per ſeruicium militare in hac forma.</q>
                  <p>Manerium de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr> cum omnibus et ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis Terris, Teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis, Pratis, Paſcuis, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ceteris ſuis iuribus, membris et perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:38"/>ſi dimitterentur xxiiii. <abbr>li.</abbr>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rectoria de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr> cum terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Glebis.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iacobus Branborne <abbr>clicus</abbr> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie de Dale xliiii. <abbr>li.</abbr>
                     </note>TEnet Rectoriam de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>, ſcituſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eiuſdem exiſtit inter Regiam viam ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr>, et cemiteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte <abbr>Oriental</abbr>, et Scitum Manerij ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et communem campum ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, et continet xxxiiii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in latitudine, et lxxxii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in longitudine, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perque Scitum <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>edificat</abbr> ſunt vna Aula, vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cenaculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> a Parlour, cum quatuor cameris, et coquina, ac vnum <abbr>ſtabul</abbr> et vnum Horreu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>cont</abbr> iii. Baies. Ac vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clauſ. terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <abbr>Occide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal</abbr> parte Pomarij, et Gardinum ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Rectorie pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>cont</abbr> vndecem acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac xxii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>arabil</abbr> de terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glebis in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni campo ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Milfelde, vnde vi. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul iacent apud Hoggeſende Ferrie ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac vnam acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacent apud Branbuſhe ibide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apud Wynleaſe &amp;c. Ac etiam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes decimas, lane, garbar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, feni et ceter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus et ſingulis proficuis, decimis, obuentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, et commoditatibus ac aduantagiis <abbr>dict</abbr> Rector<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue ſpectan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et habuit rectoriam <abbr>predict</abbr> ex donatione dicti domini Manerii <abbr>predit</abbr>, qui eſt indubitatus patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eiuſdem in iure Manerii de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr> et valet per annum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:38"/>
                  <head>Liberi Tenentes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <abbr>Willmus</abbr> at Nooke. lxii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>TEnet libe ſibi et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis de domino huius Manerii ex donatione progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini per Chartam, vnum Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuagium ſiue tenementum liberum: quod qui dem Meſſuagium ſiue tenementum iacet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rectoriam de Dale, ex parte <abbr>Occidental</abbr> et Tenementum in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> R. F. ex parte <abbr>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal</abbr> et Regiam viam ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte <abbr>Auſtral</abbr>, et communem campum ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Milne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſhe felde ex parte <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, &amp; continet xxxi perticas in longitudine, et xxii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudine. Ac etiam vnam acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prati in comuni prato voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Blithe Meade, apud le Slade ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et v. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>prat</abbr> in eodem prato apud Forough Buſh ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. Ac vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clauſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Crad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docks <abbr>cont</abbr> iiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnde vnum caput <abbr>abbutt</abbr> &amp;c. quod quidem Tenementum vocatur Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynſhedes, <abbr>quond</abbr> Iohannis Makereth, et reddit domino annuatim iiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. d. et tenet per <abbr>fidelitat</abbr> et <abbr>ſect</abbr> ad cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad duas le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas annuatim <abbr>tenend</abbr>. Et Tenementum <abbr>pred</abbr> eſt <abbr>heritabil</abbr>. &amp;c.—</p>
                  <p>
                     <abbr>Silis</abbr> intratio fiat de terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et Tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ceterorum libor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tenentium.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Tenentes ad voluntatem.</head>
                  <p>TEnet ad voluntatem Domini vnum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementum in Ribſtrete, iacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementum, S. T. ex <abbr>Oriental</abbr> parte et W. B. ex parte <abbr>occidental</abbr>, et Regia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte Auſcr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et campu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>Borial</abbr> continens xxii. <abbr>pertit</abbr> in longitudine et xxi.
<pb facs="tcp:7121:39"/>
                     <note place="margin">Iohe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Doe. xxxxiiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii.d.</note>
                     <abbr>pertit</abbr> in latitudine, cum vno Horto et Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clauſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> horſe crofte, continens octo Acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ſuper terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s P. verſus <abbr>auſtral</abbr> &amp; terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I. H. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <abbr>boreal</abbr>, &amp;c. ac vnam acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prati in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i prato ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apud Wrinehille, et quatuor acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>arabil</abbr> apud mylne Marſhe fielde, iuxta locum <abbr>vocat</abbr> Hollie acre, &amp;c. et <abbr>redd</abbr> per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num xxiiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. d. ad duos anni terminos <abbr>equal</abbr> porcoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan>. —</p>
                  <p>Silis Intratio fiat de terris et tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ceterorum tenen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad <abbr>volunt</abbr>.</p>
                  <p>Tenentes per Indentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro teri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o vite ſiue Annorum.</p>
                  <p>TEnet per Indentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>gerent</abbr> 
                     <abbr>dat</abbr> xxii. die Februarij. anno regni dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Regis nuꝑ Henrici octaui xxxiiii. vnum meſuagiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue Tenementum <abbr>ſcituat</abbr> inter regiam viam <abbr>pred</abbr> ex parte <abbr>boreal</abbr> et <abbr>Tentum</abbr> in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> R. F. ex parte <abbr>auſtral</abbr>, et coe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m campu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> ex ꝑte <abbr>occidental</abbr>, et Sowters lane ex parte <abbr>orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</abbr>, et continet in latitudine xxii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et xx. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in latitudine, et meſuagium ſiue Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum <abbr>pred</abbr> eſt ſufficienter <abbr>conſtruct</abbr>, ac etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>tegulat</abbr>, cum vno <abbr>Stabul</abbr> et vno Horreo, ac le Oxehouſe ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum Stramine <abbr>coopert</abbr>, cum vno Gardino et vno Pomario inſimul iacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>cont</abbr> duas acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vnam Rodam terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac cum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no paruo Clauſo Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <abbr>Oriental</abbr>, vnde vnum Caput <abbr>abutt</abbr>, &amp;c. Ac etiam xxiiii. Acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>err<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>arabil</abbr>, vnde. iiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacent in Mylne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſhe fielde, apud windemill hille, &amp;c. ac xi.
<pb facs="tcp:7121:39"/>
                     <note place="margin">Iohe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at Noke. Cxiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d.</note>Acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>prat</abbr>, vnde iii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vna Roda prati iacet in Broademeade, iuxta le milne da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. ac <abbr>quat</abbr> clauſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>cont</abbr> in <abbr>tot</abbr> 32 acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnde vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clauſ. iacet apud Benbowe Croſſe <abbr>cont</abbr> xiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>abbut</abbr> ſuꝑ le Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bow lane, verſ. occiden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Iohi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s M. verſus <abbr>orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</abbr>, et vnum caput eiuſdem <abbr>abut</abbr> ſuper clauſ. de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verſus <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> et alterum caput eiuſdem <abbr>abuttt</abbr> ſuper alium <abbr>croft</abbr> eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem I. M. verſus <abbr>Boreal</abbr> (&amp; ſili<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> modo de ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris) quod quidem meſuagium ſiue teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ac cetera premiſſ. cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quondam voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maliardes, modo Tournors nuꝑ, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Willi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Turnour <abbr>defunct</abbr>. <abbr>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</abbr> et <abbr>tenend</abbr> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr>. meſuagium ſiue tenementum, ac cetera p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſ. cum pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <abbr>prefat</abbr> Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i at Noke executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis a feſto ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Michaelis Archange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li vltimo preterito ante <abbr>dat</abbr> eiuſdem Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad terminum viginti, et vnius annorum, extunc proximo ſequen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; <abbr>complend</abbr>. <abbr>Reddend</abbr> inde annuatim <abbr>dict</abbr> I. S. dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>hered</abbr> et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis v. l. xiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d. ad duos anni terminos <abbr>vſual</abbr> equis porcionibus <abbr>ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uend</abbr>, duran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termino <abbr>pred.</abbr> vz. ad Feſta &amp;c. Et <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at Noke, et executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, (ex conuenco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>ſufficient</abbr> hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boote, ploughboote. &amp;c. Et <abbr>pred</abbr> I. at Noke, et excutor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui per Indentur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus reparationibus premiſſorum ad ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos ſuos proprios (grandi Maremio ſolum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo excepto) et ita ſufficienter <abbr>reꝑat</abbr> in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne termi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr>, in man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ſiue <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuorum <abbr>quiet</abbr> relinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et ſurſum reddent, ac etiam in fine termi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui predci<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabit dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o <abbr>pred</abbr>, ſeu he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redibus
<pb facs="tcp:7121:40"/>ſuis Quadraginta Solidos noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <abbr>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riott</abbr>. Ac etiam tenetur facere ſectam ad cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i quotiens legaliter <abbr>ſummo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>it</abbr> fuerit, ac etiam dabit dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o annuatim vnum Capone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vnam Gallinam ad <abbr>feſt</abbr> 
                     <abbr>natal</abbr> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, &amp;c. Et ſi reddu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <abbr>p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</abbr> areted fuerit <abbr>inſolut</abbr> in parte vel in <abbr>tot</abbr> ꝑ ſpaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſex ſeptimanaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt aliquod feſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolucon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</abbr>, et <abbr>litime</abbr> 
                     <abbr>demandat</abbr>, quod tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c licebit dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o <abbr>pred</abbr>, et heredibus ſuis in p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſ. et <abbr>quamlibt</abbr> inde <abbr>parcell</abbr> reintrar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Sili<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s intratio fiat de terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Tenementis cete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum tenentium ad voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et pro teri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, ac pro teri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o vite, ac per Copiam Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum conſuetudinem Mauerij.</p>
                  <p>Tenentes ꝑ Copiam Curie ſecundum conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem Manerij.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Enet per copia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>gerent</abbr> 
                     <abbr>dat</abbr> vndecimo die Maij. anno regni Regis nuꝑ. H. viii. xxxiiii. vnum tenementu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtumariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>abutt</abbr>, &amp;c. cuius ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti ſcitus continet in longitudine ab <abbr>orient</abbr> vſque ad <abbr>occident</abbr> xiiii. pertic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et in latitudine ab auſtro vſque ad bor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xi. perticas quod ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum cum vno Stabulo, vno Horreo, ac le Oxeſtall ſunt veter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domus et ruinoſ. cumque Stramine <abbr>coopert</abbr>. Ac etiam vnum Gardinum et vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Poma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>adiacent</abbr> in <abbr>Auſtral</abbr> parte eiuſdem ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, <abbr>cont</abbr> tres Rodas, cum vno paruo Crofto ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Pomario adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>cont</abbr> tres acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but</abbr> ſuꝑ Auſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Ac etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xxiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
<pb facs="tcp:7121:40"/>ſeptem clauſis, vnde vnum <abbr>clm</abbr> 
                     <abbr>cont</abbr> ix acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apud Ducwell ſtrete <abbr>abbut</abbr> ſuper terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> W. H. verſus Occiden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Ac etiam quatuor acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prati in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Prato ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Myulnemar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeade, apud Sande Hille, &amp;c. ac xxxi. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>arabl</abbr> in tribus coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan> Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pis pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerio <abbr>pred</abbr>, videlicet xix. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Rubro Campo. vnde tres acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et ii. furlong<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacent inſimul <abbr>apd</abbr> Shepardes Buſh ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. <abbr>qd</abbr> quidem ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum cuſtumar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod olim <abbr>vocabat</abbr> Coliers, modo Hollandes, et erat quonda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>Willm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i</abbr> Martyn <abbr>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd</abbr> et <abbr>tenend</abbr> predicto Nicholao at Stile, (ſi ſit ſibi et <abbr>hered</abbr>) dic, <abbr>hered</abbr> &amp; aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis, ſi ſit pro termino vite dic) et A vxore ſue ac I. filij eorumdem et vtriuſque eorum diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <abbr>viuent</abbr> (Si ſit pro teri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o annorum dic) executor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis pro termino xxi. anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum extunc prox. <abbr>ſequend</abbr> et plenarie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum, ad <abbr>voluntat</abbr> domini ſecundum conſue tudinem Manerii, per <abbr>redd</abbr> lxii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad <abbr>felt</abbr> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Michaelis archangeli, et Annunciationis beate Marie virgin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>annuat</abbr> 
                     <abbr>ſoluend</abbr> 
                     <abbr>equal</abbr> portionibus, et per alia ſeruicia inde prius <abbr>debit</abbr> et de iure <abbr>conſuet</abbr>: et he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus communiis domini Manerii <abbr>pred</abbr> pro quibulcunque aueriis ſuis, et tenetur per co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem Manerii <abbr>pred</abbr> omnibus repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus premiſſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ter gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Marenniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et habent Firewoode; ex conſuetudine apud boſcum domini voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eſtouer, ſuper tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                     <abbr>expendend</abbr> et non alibi, et dabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t annuatim ex conſuetudine domino Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> duas gallinas ad feſtum <abbr>natal</abbr> Domini. Ac etiam poſt mortem cuiuſlibt tenentium
<pb facs="tcp:7121:41"/>
                     <abbr>pred</abbr> dabunt dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o quilibt eorum optimum Animal nomine Herriotte, et dedit domino de fine viii. <abbr>li.</abbr> pro tali ſtatu <abbr>habend</abbr>, &amp;c. et ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſ. ſunt &amp;c. et fecer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>fidelitat</abbr> &amp;c.—</p>
                  <p>
                     <abbr>Silis</abbr> intrato fiat de terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis ceterorum tenentium per co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam curie. Sed multi ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t breuiori modo agere Intracoe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m eorum tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Communia, More et Boſci, ac Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſce <abbr>dict</abbr> Manerio de Dale pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue appenden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Communia <abbr>vocat</abbr> Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note>Magna communia ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Wymonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common, continens duo millia, et trecentas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pertinet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muniter cam dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o &amp; tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus Manerii de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>, quam dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is et te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus Maneriorum de H. et C. dicto Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio de Dale adiacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue contingen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Communia <abbr>vocat</abbr> Marſhmore</note>Alia communia <abbr>vocat</abbr> Marſhemore, continens quadringentas acras terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proprie Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o et tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus huius Manerii de Dale, et exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit ſe a le Roſſes woode in <abbr>Orient</abbr>, vſque Halliers Ponde in Occiden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ver le Auſter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Boſcus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> le Eſtouer.</note>Boſcus communis ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> le Eſtouer magna, pertinet proprie domino Manerii de Dale predict, et tenentibus eiuſdem tam pro reparatione ceuementorum ſuorum, quam pro le Fewell eorundem ex <abbr>conſuetud</abbr>, &amp; <abbr>extend</abbr> ab Mores Lake, verſus <abbr>Orient</abbr> ad Blande marle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitte
<pb facs="tcp:7121:41"/>
verſus Occiden<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et a Graies doune Lane, verſus Auſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſque Banierdes Shaue, verſus <abbr>Boreal</abbr>, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <abbr>Silis</abbr> fiat intratio de horum <abbr>ſilibus</abbr>.</p>
                  <p>And thus muche breefly for the engroſſemente of a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey and terrour, obſeruyng as well the Rules, as formes of entries afore ſpecified, maie well ſuffice.</p>
                  <p>Note alſo, diuerſe men addicted to their owne fantaſies and mindes, do vſe diuerſe other formes, in makyng of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyes and terrours, whoſe doynges like as I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne, ſo I truſte thei will not of their gentleneſſe muche carpe at this, ſette out of good will for enſtruction, onely of ſuche as be ignoraunte in that facultie.</p>
                  <p>But yet before I leaue treatyng hereof, I thinke good to put you in remembraunce, that one ſpeciall pointe bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, in the entryng of all parcelles, that (by ſearchyng of the aunciente Euidences, Recordes, Bookes of Surueye, and Terrours of any Mannour, he doe as nere as he can, in his newe entrie in the Surueye booke or Terrour, at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſyng thereof, ſpecifie it, and enter the olde ſeuerall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of euery Tenemente, Cloſe, or ſuche: and alſo the names of ſuche olde Tenauntes as helde the ſame before, aſwell as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of them that holde it at this preſente daie, and ſpecially of the landes of freeholders, and this principall obſeruation will not onely wonderfully preſerue memorie, but alſo exclude doubtes, and be occaſion from tyme to tyme to greate quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. A breef enſample whereof enſueth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iohannes Doo.</note>Tenet lib<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e de domino huius Manerii per Charta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſibi et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis, (if it bee by Copie, ſaie) per Copiam <abbr>cut</abbr> &amp;c. vnum Meſuagium ſiue Tenementum cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. olim <abbr>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat</abbr>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:42"/>
Shanckes, poſtea Shangrelles, et modo Tremors, olim in tenur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>Willmi</abbr> Shanck et poſtea Edmundi Tremour, et nuper Briani Tyſon &amp;c.—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>¶ A bye Rule.</hi> Regula Apportionation<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terrarum ſecundum <abbr>reddit</abbr> eiuſdem.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Surueiours vſe, ſome time to portionate the rente of euery Tenauntes holdyng, accordyng to the number, quantitie, and qualitie of the lande that he holdeth after the acre. That he maie thereby the better perceiue what euery Tenaunte commonly paieth for an acre, bee it Lande, Meadowe, Paſture, or woode, after the ſtinte of his rente, and if it be better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rente, then there by he vnderſtandeth how muche more rente euery Acre is yerely worthe.</p>
                  <p>But this enſtruction with other ſome before ſpecified, ſhould not be made to common emongſt thoſe perſones, who are ouergredie coueteous, that care not how thei racke their Tenauntes, to their owne dampnation, leaſte thei abuſe the ſame, to the oppreſſyng of their Tenauntes. Yet ye ſhal haue here a breefe example thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vppoſe a Tenaunt holdeth a Meeſe or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, with Garden and Orchard, and twentie Acres of Paſture, thirtie Acres of arable, and fowertine Acres of Meadowe, (as for the wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, vnleſſe it bee in thoſe Mannours where it is lawfull for the Tenaunt to fell it, or after the ſame being ſtubbed, is made into Paſture, &amp;c. is ſeldome vſed to be rated or apportionated.) And he paieth for all the ſame lx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. yerely.
<pb facs="tcp:7121:42"/>
Now if it be knowen how muche of the ſaide Rente is yerely pated for the Paſture, howe muche for the errable, and howe muche for the Meadowe diſtinctly, either by ſeuerall reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in tymes paſt, or how they were ſeuerally let heretofore, it were ſoone doone. (As for the Houſe, Garden or Orcharde where there is aboue thirty or fiue and twenty Acres of land belongyng to it, in this kynde of apportionatyng, is ſeldome or neuer rated or apportionated) but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Land, Meadow and Paſture onely. Then is the rate of the Lande aforeſaide, in this maner apportionated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2 In Paſture— xx. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.—Rent xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The acre xij. d. —</cell>
                           <cell>Acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. liiij.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1 In errable —xxx. acres. Rent xv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The acre vi. d.—</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3 In Meadowe xiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Rent xxv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The acre xxj. d. ob.</cell>
                           <cell>Rent lx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Carens i. d. in toto.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some write their Rate or Apportionation in this fourme followyng.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Acre <abbr>reddus</abbr> quelibet acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2 In Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>xx. —xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.— xii. d.</cell>
                           <cell>Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma acrar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>—liiii</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1 In terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>arabil</abbr>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>xxx.—xv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.—vi. d.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3 In Prato.</cell>
                           <cell>xiiii.—xxv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xxj. d. ob</cell>
                           <cell>Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma <abbr>reddus</abbr>— lx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>Carens i. d. in toto.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus where the Rente is ſeuerally reſerued for euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or kinde of lande a ſeuerall certaine rente, it may eaſely as ye ſee, be rated or aportionated. And if this bee the caſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuyng as it moſt comonly chaunceth, that the ſeuerall rentes are vncertaine.</p>
                  <p>As a Tenaunt holdeth a tenement and twenty foure acres errable, twelue acres Paſture, and eight acres meadowe, or ſuch like, now to rate or apportionate the ſame is ſomewhat difficulte. And before ye can make any ſubſtanciall apportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Ye muſt partly knowe the goodnes and fruitfulnes or
<pb facs="tcp:7121:43"/>
fertillity of euery ſuche lande, Meadowe and Paſture. For in ſuche a place the ſame maye lye that the errable is not worth iiii. d. an acre, but leſſe, and in ſuche place it may lye, that an acre errable is worth xii. d. xvi. d. yea xx. d. an acre and more. And in like maner the Paſture may lye in ſome place, that it is worthe iii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d. or iiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or more, an acre, and in ſome place liyng againe it is worthe ſcante xii. d. an acre or leſſe. The Meadow likewiſe may lye in ſome ſuche place, that it is worth yerely vi.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. d. x.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. yea xiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d. or xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. an acre, beyng encloſed and lowe grounde. And againe in ſome place it may ſo lye, that it may bee to deare of v.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. an acre, either for that it is baren, or lieth high, or liyng lowe and fenny, it may be full of Ruſhes, Flagges, or knotgraſſe. And all theſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of grounde may bee ſometyme in one Mannour. Yea ſometyme belongyng to one Tenement. Therefore in this, and ſuche like caſes the rent muſt be apportionated after the goodnes, and badneſſe, of the kindes of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, accordyng on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the prudente diſcretion of the Surueiour, without a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, or if ye will needes deſire, a certaine fourme to apportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſuche vncertainties (as moſte men dooe couet to haue a certainty preſcribed in euery thing) Then let this following be your waye, or meane, which I haue knowen ſome men vſe, called a ſuppoſition pro incerto, as they tearme it.</p>
                  <p>Apportionate the rente in the ſecond caſe aforeſaide, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lottyng firſt to euery acre of the arrable xii. d. an acre, let this be the roote nowe, or foundation. Then allotte vpon euery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of Paſture alwaies double aſmuche and halfe as muche, as is allotted vpon an acre errable, and then is here euery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of paſture ii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allot vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery acre of Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe foure tymes as muche and halfe as muche as is allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo vpon any acre errable, which as the number of acres of meadowe doe ariſe here, is fower ſhillynges ſixe pence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the acre, as thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:43"/>
                     <item>In terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>arabil</abbr> xxiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>reddit</abbr> xxiiii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. quelib<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xii. d. ſum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xliiii ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>redd</abbr>. 4. <abbr>l</abbr> x.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                     <item>In Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>— xii.acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>reddit</abbr> xxx.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.—quelib<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. ſum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xliiii ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>redd</abbr>. 4. <abbr>l</abbr> x.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                     <item>In <abbr>Prat</abbr>—viii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <abbr>reddit</abbr> xxxvi.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. queli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bt acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iiii.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. ſum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xliiii ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <abbr>redd</abbr>. 4. l. x.s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>This maner of apportionatyng ſome doe vſe when they would redily ſee a preſent apportionacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (although, nere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beyng vncertayne, becauſe it is founded vpon a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition vncertaine. But the beſt and ſureſt waie is to make the apportionatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies by the knowledge and diſcretion that is to ſay accordyng to the goodnes and fertilitie of the lande, and ſeldome otherwiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="rule">
               <head>¶The ſixt Rule. ¶The fourme how a Suite Rolle ſhoulde be engroſſed and kepte.</head>
               <p>Libi. Tenentes qui debent annual a ſecta ad Leta et cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baron<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manerij de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>.</p>
               <p>HEnricus at Noke, pro lib<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o <abbr>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt</abbr> ſuo in Halſtrete, cum pertim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idem. Henricus pro vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crofto <abbr>vocat</abbr> Peches woode.</p>
               <p>
                  <abbr>Willms</abbr> Boothe pro vno Horreo et xiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde.</p>
               <p>Edmundus Brainthorpe pro vno prato iuxta Hobbes mede.</p>
               <p>
                  <abbr>Silis</abbr> fiat intracio de his <abbr>ſili<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>bus</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </abbr>, ſed ſi ſunt ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem cum dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Manerij reddere <abbr>annual</abbr> fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certum, pro ſectis ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr>, tunc intitulatur illa finis in margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſuper caput eiuſdem in hac forma.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Finis ꝓ <abbr>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual</abbr> 
                     <abbr>ſect</abbr> 12. <abbr>d</abbr>
                  </note> Richardus Moreton pro vno Tenemento cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in le Scadeſborne f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te et ſic de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eteris.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="rule">
               <pb facs="tcp:7121:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>¶The ſeuenth Rule.</hi> The forme and inſtruction how to engroſſe, and kepe a cuſtomarie Rolle of a Mannour.</head>
               <p>Cuſtionar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue <abbr>Rotul</abbr> omnium et ſingulorum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumariorum in Manerio de Dale <abbr>pred</abbr>, de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore ex quo non extat memoria hominum ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>vſitat</abbr> et <abbr>approbat</abbr>, <abbr>fact</abbr>, <abbr>renouat</abbr> ac <abbr>indentat</abbr> inter du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m Manerii <abbr>predex</abbr> vna parte ac tenentes eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex altera ꝑte. x. Auguſti anno &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Maneriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Dale.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>ST quedam antiqua conſuetudo infra Manerium <abbr>predict</abbr>, quod nullus Tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium eiuſdem Manerij poteſt dimittere Tenementum ſuum cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquam inde parcellam alicui extraneo qui <abbr>habit</abbr> extra limites huius Manerii, niſi ſolummodo alicui tenenti infra Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerium <abbr>pred</abbr>, ſine licentia domini, ac etiam non dimittet tali tenenti neque, niſi pro termino vnius anni, et ſic de anno in annum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne licentia domini, ſub pena foriſfactur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtatus ſui in Tenemento <abbr>pred</abbr>, vel <abbr>parcell</abbr> terr ſic dimiſſ, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Ac etiam quod null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s tenentium Manerii <abbr>pred</abbr> decidet, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ender aliquos Boſcos ſuper tenementum ſuum cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel aliquam parcellam eidem Tenemento pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, creſcen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſine licentia domini, ſub pena <abbr>pred</abbr> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Acetiam quod vnumquodque tenementum pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huic manerio eſt <abbr>herietabil</abbr> et dominus manerii <abbr>pred</abbr> Seiſabit in manus ſuas proprias ad op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuum vnumquodque optimum animal quod aliquis tene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> habuit tempore mortis ſue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <abbr>heriott</abbr> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:44"/>Item vnuſquiſque tenentium tenetur per <abbr>conſuetud</abbr> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta ſua in omnibus ad ſumptus ſuos proprios de tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in tempus ſufficienter reparare et manutenere in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus reparationibus preter grande maremium ſub penaforiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fact <abbr>pred</abbr> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Ac etiam vnuſquiſque tenentium tenetur, per conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem eiuſdem maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> antiquam, dare domino annuatim in feſt natalis domini duos Capones, et in feſto Pentecoſtes tres Anſeres &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Et <abbr>ſilis</abbr> fiat intratio de ceteris cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alicui Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio quocunque ſpectan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="rule">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶The eight Rule.</hi> The forme and maner how to make a true and perfecte ready Rentall of a Mannour, when the ſame ſhall bee deliuered to any Bailife, Reue, or Collectour to gather by.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Entale</hi> Iohannis at Stile militis,<note place="margin">Maneriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Dale.</note> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr> ibidem <abbr>renouat</abbr> &amp; <abbr>examinat</abbr> decimo die Decembr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Anno regni domine noſtre Elizabeth, Dei gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Anglie &amp;c. Regine tertio, per A. G. Superuiſor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini <abbr>pred</abbr>, <abbr>Soluend</abbr> ad feſta Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciationis beate Marie vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis, et Sancti Michaelis Archangeli, annuatim equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. vz.</p>
               <p>
                  <abbr>Reddit</abbr> aſſil. liberorum Tenentium.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>De Anthonio Milles pro libo Reddu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius tenti in Southelake cum <abbr>cert</abbr> 
                     <abbr>parcell</abbr> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eidem tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:45"/>D' Auguſtino Northall pro <abbr>libo</abbr> 
                     <abbr>Redd</abbr> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius croft ibidem <abbr>vocat</abbr> Paſtours, continen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>D' <abbr>Hered</abbr> Iohannis Hutton pro <abbr>libo</abbr> reddu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius meſſuagij cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et <abbr>cert</abbr> percel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Harſton, infra manerium <abbr>pred</abbr> per annum. xxiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. d. ob.</item>
                  <item>Sum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>Redd</abbr> 
                     <abbr>liborum</abbr> tenentium xli. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. d. ob.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <abbr>Reddit</abbr> aſſiſ. ſcitus Manerij cum terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominicalibus.</head>
                  <item>D'Ambroſio Stouer firmar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcitus Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij <abbr>predict</abbr> cum diuerſis terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, prac<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominicalibus per annum. xxxviii. l. xix. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>D'Richardo Morriſin firmario vnius clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>dominical</abbr> 
                     <abbr>vocat</abbr> Cowleaſe, <abbr>cont</abbr> xl acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per annum. vii. <abbr>li.</abbr> ii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>Summa <abbr>Reddit</abbr> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icalium. xlvi. <abbr>li.</abbr> xii. d.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <abbr>Reddit</abbr> aſſiſ. Cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tenen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem.</head>
                  <item>D' <abbr>Willmo</abbr> Bortmocher pro <abbr>redd</abbr> 
                     <abbr>tenti</abbr> ſui cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per annum. iiii. <abbr>li.</abbr> xii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>D' Iohanne Tirlynger pro <abbr>redd</abbr> teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti ſui cuſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per annum. iii. <abbr>li.</abbr> ii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>D' Henrico Marſhe pro <abbr>redd</abbr> Tenementi ſui cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tilers. iii. <abbr>li.</abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>D' Briano Barret pro <abbr>redd</abbr> vnius Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martens. xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:45"/>D' Oſwaldo Barton, pro <abbr>redd</abbr> Tenementi ſui cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertinen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xxxiiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>D' Rogero Marlebrough pro Tenemento ſuo cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Wrangles. xviii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>Sum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>redd</abbr> cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xv. <abbr>li.</abbr> ii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>Summa <abbr>total</abbr> 
                     <abbr>Rental</abbr> 
                     <abbr>pred.</abbr> lxiii. l. iiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. d. ob.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Memorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that in like forme, as I haue ſhewed you by the example of this Rentall, ſo maie you doe in all other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="rule">
               <head>The ninth Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue vnder correction partlye ſet out, (although maiſter Fitzhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert hath ſhewed many good four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes already) certaine fourmes of ſuche eſtates by copy hold, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the leauiyng of a Fyne and recouerie in a cuſtumarie Court for Barryng of an Entaile of Cuſtumarie Landes, not at any tyme heretofore els publiſhed, whiche was of the diligent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte penning of the late right worſhipfull and wel learned Maiſter Iuſtice Staunforde, late one of the Iuſtices of the common Bench at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, accordyng to the copie &amp; true report thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>D cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manerij ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr> die Mercurij proxim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt feſtum Apoſtolorum Philippi et Iacobi,<note place="margin">Surſum <abbr>redd</abbr> in ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na curia.</note> Anno, &amp;c. ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. T. B. et Surſ. <abbr>redd</abbr> in Man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i in plena cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnum tenementum <abbr>ſcituat</abbr> in wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane <abbr>abbutt</abbr> ſuper Tentm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I.B. ex parte <abbr>Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental</abbr>, &amp;c. xxiiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prati et Paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus et vſum I.L. et Hered. ſuorum, qui preſens hic in cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit
<pb facs="tcp:7121:46"/>
admitti ad premiſ. cui Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s per Seneſcallum ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit inde Seia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m: habendum et tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum ſibi, et Heredibus ſuis de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o per virgam ad voluntatem domini,<note place="margin">Finis.</note> ſecundum conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem Manerij per <abbr>reddit</abbr> et <abbr>ſeruit</abbr> inde prius <abbr>debit</abbr>, et de iure <abbr>conſuet</abbr>, et dat dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o de fine prout <abbr>pꝪ</abbr> in margine, et fecit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitatem et admiſſus eſt inde tenens.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Surſ. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is.</note>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr>, &amp;c. Homag<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>preſent</abbr> quod H.H. qui de Domino tenuit ſibi et heredibus ſuis reuerſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. infra iſtud maneriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quorum I.H. vidua eſt tee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns ad terminum vite ſue, diem clauſit extremum, poſt vltimam Curiam. Et quod R.H. eius Auunculus eſt illi heres, ſcilicet frater Thome H. pris<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> H.H. et eſt plene etatis, qui prn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hic in Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> petit admitti ad reuerſionem terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> I. H. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <abbr>dit.</abbr> H.H. vt <abbr>ſupradict</abbr> eſt, cui dominus per ſen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit inde Seia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m: habendum et tenendum ſibi et heredibus ſuis ſecundum conſuetudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Manerij <abbr>pred</abbr> per <abbr>redd</abbr> et <abbr>ſeruit</abbr> inde prius <abbr>debit</abbr>,<note place="margin">Finis.</note> &amp;c. et dat domino de fine prout <abbr>pꝪ</abbr>, &amp;c. et fecit fidelitatem et admiſſus eſt inde tenens.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vbi mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus tenet in iure vxoris et vbi eis relaxetur per alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr>, &amp;c. comꝑtum eſt per Homagium quod W.H. poſt vltim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Surſ. <abbr>redd</abbr> in manus dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnum tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. &amp;c. infra iſtud Manerium ad opus et vſum. M. vxis<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuorum. Et ſuper hoc ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in plena Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I.H. qui iam <abbr>dict</abbr> 
                  <abbr>Margaret</abbr> in vxorem duxit cum <abbr>predict</abbr> M. et petunt admitti ad premiſ. quibus dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s per Seneſcallum ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceſſit eis inde Seia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m. Habendum et tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum eis, et <abbr>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</abbr> dicte Margarete de Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o per virgam ad <abbr>voluntat</abbr> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, ſcdm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudinem Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> per <abbr>redd</abbr> et ſeruicia, &amp;c. Et dat dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o de fine. &amp;c. et fecit fidelitatem, &amp;c. Et admiſ. ſunt inde <abbr>tenent.</abbr> Et poſtea ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. T. Et Surſ. <abbr>redd</abbr>, relaxauit et <abbr>quiet</abbr> clamauit <abbr>dict</abbr> I. H. et Margaret vxor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius in plena et pacifica poſſeſſione exiſten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de et in tenementis <abbr>pred</abbr> totum ius, ſtatum, titulum, clameu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, intereſſe conditiones et <abbr>demand</abbr> ſua quecunque hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>it he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſeu hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit de et in ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, &amp;c. Ita vt <note place="margin">Finis.</note>nec prefat S.T. <abbr>Hered</abbr> ſeu aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui poſt hac aliquod ius cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7121:46"/>
ſeu <abbr>demand</abbr> de et in premiſ. aut aliqua inde ꝑcella exige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſeu vendicare poterint, vel poterit. Sed ab omni acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne iuris, tituli, et intereſſe inde <abbr>petend</abbr> penitus ſint excluſi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpetuum per preſentes. <abbr>hend</abbr> &amp;c. vt ſupra.</p>
               <p>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Vbi Heres <abbr>redempt</abbr> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <abbr>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pignorat</abbr> per pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m.</note> &amp;c. compertum eſt per Homagium quod R. P. eſt filius et heres, H.P. qui quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> R.P. ingreſ. <abbr>cert</abbr> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Que dudum <abbr>impignorat</abbr> fuerunt. I P. et iam <abbr>redempt</abbr> ſunt per I.A. qui mr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em dicti R. in vxorem duxit. Et ſic idem R. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus eſt terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>prediure</abbr> hereditar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at poſt deceſſum. H. <abbr>pred</abbr> vt filius et heres <abbr>dict.</abbr> H. cui quidem Rico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s per Seneſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum fuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceſſit inde ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Habendum et tenendum ſibi et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o per virgam ad voluntatem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, ſecundum conſuetudinem Manerii per <abbr>redd</abbr>. &amp;c. Et dat dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o de fine, &amp;c. Et fecit, &amp;c. et admiſ. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent.</abbr> &amp;c. venit. I. T. nuper <abbr>relict</abbr>. I.T. viri ſui <abbr>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct</abbr>,<note place="margin">Relaxaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dotis vidue poſt morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viri ſui.</note> et <abbr>pretend</abbr> her<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <abbr>titl</abbr> in vna domo. &amp;c. vi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>z. tertiam parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnium terrarum et tenementorum <abbr>reddit</abbr>, &amp; <abbr>ſeruit</abbr> cum ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Dotis ſue ex Dotatione <abbr>dict</abbr> I. T. viri ſui, et pro quadam pecuniarum Sum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a ſibi per <abbr>Willm</abbr> A. pre manibus <abbr>ſolut</abbr> ſurſum <abbr>redd</abbr>, remiſit, et relaxauit totum ius ſuum, ſtatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, titulum clameu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intereſſe et <abbr>demand</abbr> ſua quecunque, que hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>it, he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeu hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit in premiſ. Ita <abbr>videll</abbr> quod nec ipſa Iohanna nec <abbr>hered</abbr> ſui, nec aliquis alius noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſuo vel eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aliquod ius. flatum, <abbr>titlm</abbr>, clameum intereſſe ſeu <abbr>demand</abbr> de et in premiſ. vel aliqua inde parcella exigere, vel vendicare poterint. Sed ab omni acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Iuris, ſtatus, tituli, intereſſe,<note place="margin">Licentia dimittendi terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> ſed <abbr>demand</abbr> peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſint excluſi imꝑꝑuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per preſentes.</p>
               <p>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr>, &amp;c. conceditur R.H. vidue, poteſtas, et li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia <abbr>dimittend</abbr> vnum clauſ. paſtur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. N. vz. cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et exiſten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infra iſtud Menerium. T.P. et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, &amp;c. vltim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>preterit</abbr>, vſque ad finem Termini xxi. annorum,<note place="margin">Finis.</note> tunc proxime <abbr>ſequend</abbr> &amp; <abbr>complend</abbr>. Et dat Domino de fine pro licentia inde <abbr>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd</abbr> vt <abbr>pꝪ</abbr> in margine.<note place="margin">Pro terio vite.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Ad hanc Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I.H. et R. vxor eius, ipſa ſola <abbr>exai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ata</abbr> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram
<pb facs="tcp:7121:47"/>
ſeneſcallo, et ſurſum <abbr>redd</abbr> in manus dm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnum tenement cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter <abbr>tenement</abbr> F. H. &amp;c. ad opus et vſum G. H. &amp; I vxor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius ad terminum vite eorum, et alterius eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diutius viuen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Finis.</note> ſecundum conſuetudinem Mauerij, et dant domino de fin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. et f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. et admiſ. ſunt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Surſ. redd. ſuꝑ condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>Ad Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr> &amp;c. venit I.H. et Surſ. <abbr>redd</abbr> in manus domini vnum tenementum, &amp;c. <abbr>abbutt</abbr>, &amp;c. ad opus et vſum R. F. &amp;c. <abbr>hend</abbr> et <abbr>tenend</abbr> ſibi et heredibus ſuis, de domino ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem domini <abbr>ſcdm</abbr>, &amp;c. ſub conditionibus ſequentibus, <abbr>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delt</abbr> ſi <abbr>pred</abbr> R. F. ſoluat, aut ſolui faciat prefato, I.H. xx. <abbr>li</abbr>. ad feſta infraſcripta vi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>z, &amp;c. et ad <abbr>feſt</abbr> &amp;c. proxim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> futur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum huius curie, quod tunc prius ſurſum <abbr>redd</abbr>, ſit in ſuo ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore et effectu. Et ſi ipſe defecerit in ſolutione ſolutionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr>. in parte vel in toto, &amp;c. quod tunc bene licebit I.H. <abbr>pred</abbr> et aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis reincrare in premiſ. et ea rehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re, iſta ſurſum <abbr>redd</abbr> in aliquo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſtan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Et dat domino de fin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. et fecit <abbr>fidelitat</abbr>, &amp;c. Et admiſſus eſt. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vbi dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cedit pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cum clauſ. repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>AD Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem <abbr>tent</abbr> &amp;c. Dominus per A. B. Seneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callum ſuum conceſſit R. F. vnum meſſuagium cum domibus edificiis &amp;c. ac ceteris ſuis pertm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>vocat</abbr>. N. <abbr>hend</abbr> et <abbr>tenend</abbr> ſibi et aſſign<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis a feſto ſancti Michaelis Archangeli, vltimo preterito ante <abbr>dat</abbr> huius Curie, vſque ad finem et terminum xxi. annorum, extunc proxime ſequen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et plenarie <abbr>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plend</abbr>. <abbr>Reddend</abbr> inde annuatim dicto domino, et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad quatuor anni terminos viz, ad feſta &amp;c. per equales portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. Prouiſo ſemper, quod duran<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termino <abbr>pred</abbr> dominus inueniet gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de maremium, totiens quotiens neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium fuerit dicto tenemento, ad <abbr>emendend</abbr>, <abbr>reparand</abbr>, et <abbr>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinend</abbr>, et <abbr>dat</abbr> domino de fine &amp;c. Et fecit fidelitatem &amp;c. Et admiſſ. eſt &amp;c.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="form">
                           <head>The forme of a Copie for terme of thrée liues, as it is commonly vſed in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties of Deuon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Corn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Somerſ. Dorſſ. &amp;c. where the Tenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:7121:47"/>
take their holdynges of the lettyng of the Surueyour. &amp;c.</head>
                           <p>AD Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>tent</abbr> &amp;c. venit I.G. et cepit de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o ex traditione R.F. Armiger<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Maneriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de Sale.</note> ꝑticular<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperuiſor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum domini ibm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. per literas eiuſdem domini paten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>ſufficient</abbr> 
                              <abbr>autorizat</abbr>, <abbr>dat</abbr> &amp;c. vnum teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <abbr>cont</abbr> xxxvi. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et iiii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>prat</abbr> 
                              <abbr>abuttat</abbr> &amp;c. <abbr>habend</abbr>, et <abbr>tenend</abbr> oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a &amp; ſingula premiſſ. cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuis pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>prefat</abbr>. I.G. &amp; Elizabeth vxori eius, ac <abbr>Agnet</abbr> filie <abbr>eorumdm</abbr> ad terminum vite eorum et alterius eorum diutius viuen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſucceſſiue, ad voluntatem dm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum conſuetudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, per <abbr>redd</abbr> et ſeruic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inde prius <abbr>debit</abbr> et de iure <abbr>conſuet</abbr>. Et <abbr>dat</abbr> domino de fine xxiiii.<note place="margin">Finis 24 l.</note> 
                              <abbr>li</abbr>. <abbr>ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uend</abbr>, ad manus Balliui Manerii <abbr>pred</abbr>, ad iiii. proxim<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>put</abbr> equaliter &amp;c. Et fecit <abbr>fidelitat</abbr> &amp;c. Et admiſſus<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt. &amp;c.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="form">
                           <head>An exacte forme of a Recouerie of Copieholde lande, for barryng of annuitie, <abbr>fact</abbr> et dimiſſ. per W. Staung.</head>
                           <p>AD hanc Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>tent</abbr> &amp;c. Ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I.H. filius W.H. de S. in propr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſona ſua,<note place="margin">Querela quedam de recupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note> et quer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verſus I. A. filium et <abbr>hered</abbr> W. A. <abbr>defunct</abbr> in <abbr>plito</abbr> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>videlt</abbr> de vno tenemento, et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; <abbr>heriott</abbr> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Welles, ac vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> B. et T. <abbr>pred</abbr> infra iuriſdictionem huius Curie, et fecit proteſtationem proſequi querelam iſtam, in natura bris<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini Regis de <abbr>ingr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>id</abbr> ſuper diſſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>amin le poſt ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em legem, et inuen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plegios de <abbr>proſequend</abbr> querelam ſuam, Iohannem Do, et Ricardu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Roo, et petit proceſſ. inde ei fieri verſus <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohannem A. ſecundum <abbr>conſuetud</abbr> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erga proximam Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hic infra Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                              <abbr>tenend</abbr>. Et ei conceditur: ſuper quo preceptum eſt W. T. <abbr>Ballio</abbr> Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>pred</abbr>, at miniſtr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huius cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod Summone at per bonos Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monitor<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>prefat</abbr> I. quod. ſic hic ad proximam Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <abbr>tenend</abbr>: ad
<pb facs="tcp:7121:48"/>
                              <abbr>reſpondend</abbr> 
                              <abbr>prefat</abbr> I.H. de <abbr>plito</abbr> 
                              <abbr>pred</abbr>.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Forma re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curia.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>D hanc Curiam ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tam I.H. quam Iohannes A. et <abbr>Willmus</abbr> T. Balliuus domini Manerii <abbr>pred</abbr>, ac miniſter huius Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et retorn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod preceptum ſuum ad vltimam Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi <abbr>direct</abbr> in omnibus <abbr>ſeruit</abbr> &amp; <abbr>execut</abbr> ſuper quo ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohannes H. in propria perſona ſua, et per li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam domini petit verſus <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohannem A. vnum tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtumar<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et <abbr>herriott</abbr> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in T. <abbr>pred</abbr> infra iuriſdictionem huius Curie, vt ius et heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſuam: et in quam idem I. A. non habet ing<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> niſi per diſſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am quam Hugo Hunt, inde iniuſte et ſine iudicio fecit <abbr>prefat</abbr> I.H. infra quinquaginta annos, iam vltime elapſos. Et vnde dicit quod ipſe fuit ſeiſitus de <abbr>pred</abbr> teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, et xviii acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in T. <abbr>pred</abbr> in dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ico ſuo, vt de <abbr>feod</abbr> et iure, tempore pacis te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Regis H. viii. nuper Regis Anglie pris<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domine Regine nunc, <abbr>capiend</abbr> inde exples<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam &amp;c. et in que &amp;c. Et inde produt<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſectam &amp;c. et <abbr>pred</abbr> I. A. in propria perſona ſua ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et <abbr>defend</abbr> ius ſuum quando &amp;c. Et vocat inde ad <abbr>Warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tizand</abbr> W. R. qui preſens eſt hic in Curia in propria perſona, et <abbr>grat</abbr> 
                  <abbr>tenement</abbr> et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> ei warrantiz. Et ſuper hoc predictus Iohannes, petit verſus ipſum W. Rede ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per <abbr>Warrant</abbr> ſuum tenementum et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in forma <abbr>pred</abbr> &amp;c. Et vnde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit quod ipſemet fuit ſeiſitus de tenemento <abbr>pred</abbr>, et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dominice ſuo vt de <abbr>feod</abbr>, et iure, tempore pacis, tempore domini Regis H. viii. nuper Regis Anglie pris<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domine Regine nunc, <abbr>capiend</abbr> inde <abbr>exples</abbr> ad valentiam &amp;c. et in que &amp;c. inde produc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſectam &amp;c. Et <abbr>predict</abbr> W. Rede ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per Warrentiam ſuam <abbr>defend</abbr> ius ſuum quando &amp;c. Et poſtea idem Iohannes H. reuenit hic in Curia iſta in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria perſona ſua, &amp; <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                  <abbr>Wilmus</abbr> Rede licet <abbr>ſolempnit</abbr> exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non reuenit ſed in <abbr>contempt</abbr> Curie receſſit, et defaltum fecit, ideo conceſſum eſt per curiam quod <abbr>pred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</abbr> I. H. recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret
<pb facs="tcp:7121:48"/>
ſeiam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de <abbr>pred</abbr> teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, &amp; xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <abbr>prefat</abbr> Iohannem A. Et quod idem Iohannes A. habeat de terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et tenementis <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                  <abbr>Willmi</abbr> Rede, infra Manerium <abbr>pred</abbr> ad valentiam &amp;c. Et idem <abbr>Willmus</abbr> Rede ſit in mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a. Et ſuper hoc in iſta eadem Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohannes H. et hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer petit quod ipſum Iohannem ad <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                  <abbr>tenement</abbr>, et octodecim acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cultum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum formam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperationis <abbr>pred</abbr> admittere dignaretur. Et ſuper hoc du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s per ſeneſcallum ſuum conceſſit <abbr>prefat</abbr> Iohanni et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am premiſſorum cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>tenend</abbr> ſibi et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis <abbr>quiet</abbr> de <abbr>prefat</abbr> Iohanne A. et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis imꝑpum<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Recuperationis <abbr>pred</abbr> de dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o per virgam ad volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatem domini ſecundum conſuetudinem Maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> per <abbr>reddit</abbr> &amp;c. et dat domino de fine &amp;c. Et poſtea in eadem Cur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ven<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>pred</abbr> Iohannes, et Dorothea vxor eius, ipſaque Dorothea per ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcallum ſola examinata et confeſſ. per <abbr>ſurſumredd</abbr> remiſer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et relaxauer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <abbr>prefat</abbr> Iohanni H. et <abbr>hered</abbr> ſuis totum ius ſuum <abbr>ſtat</abbr>, titulum, clameum, intereſſe, &amp; <abbr>demand</abbr> ſua quecunque que habent hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erunt, vel in futur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re poterint in <abbr>pred</abbr> 
                  <abbr>tent</abbr>, et xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum pertin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ita videlicet quod nec ipſi Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, et Dorothea, nec heredes ſui, nec aliquis alius nomine eorum, aliquod ius vel clameum in <abbr>pred</abbr> ten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ec xviii. acr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de cetero exigere, vel vendicare poterit, vel poterint, ſed ab omni actione Iur<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel clamei ſint excluſ. et <abbr>quilt</abbr> eorum ſit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ. per preſentes. Et dat domino de fine pro relaxatione <abbr>pred</abbr>.—xiii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d.</p>
               <p>And now thus muche maie at this tyme ſuffice, touchyng the entrie of the eſtates of Copie holde Landes, if ye will ſee more, I referre you to maſter Fitz Harberts woorke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="rule">
               <pb facs="tcp:7121:49"/>
               <head>The tenth Rule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe it is partely appertaining to the Office of a Surueiour, to haue ſome vnderſtandyng in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuryng and meating of Lande and wood grounde, and how to reduce the ſame into true Contentes and numbers of Acres, as often and when as occaſion ſhal require: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they that deſire the ful and perfecte knowledge thereof, may reade the ſame out of the aunciente Bookes of <hi>Architas</hi> and <hi>Archimedes,</hi> or of worthy <hi>Euclides</hi> treatyng of the whole ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Geometrie, or els for this parte Geometricall, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for meaſuryng of Landes, the Booke of Richarde Beneſe, late Chanon of Marton, and the Tectonicon of maiſter Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narde Digges our Countreiman, verie well ſett out in our daies: Although I might (I ſay) leaue men to thoſe Bookes for their inſtruction in this matter, where as they may learne twentie partes more then I can enfourme them: Yet becauſe fewe men are ripe therein, neither the ſame Bookes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies at hande at nedefull tymes when occaſion requireth, I haue therfore thought good, leauyng and paſſyng ouer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable number of examples, (and alſo the Geometricall Inſtrument or Staffe vntouched) onely hereunto to annexe, and ſet out in briefe maner, for the Surueiours better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: firſte, the partes whereinto an Acre is deuided: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, a fewe plaine examples amongeſte manye, for meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of Land, and Wood, aſwell Hilles as Vallies, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently conſidered and peruſed by any willynge or ſenſible parſon, he may with practiſe, ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vnderſtande the true meaſuryng of all maner of parcelles of Landes and Wodds whatſoeuer. And ſpecially thou ſhalt haue alſo (Gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)
<pb facs="tcp:7121:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the ende thereof, a ready and fruitfull Table for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of Landes, much more amplified then Digges Table is. Onely deſiryng this of thée, Gentle Reader, whatſoeuer thou be, that howe ſoeuer my ſimple labour ſhall like thée, yet, without any detractyng or diſpraiſe, to accept in good parte my willyng induſtrie.</p>
               <div type="table">
                  <head>¶The Partes or Diuiſions of one Acre with the Denominations of the ſame, accordyng to the Statute here mentioned.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Thrée Barley cornes faire and rounde, taken out of the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Eare, maketh an Inche.</item>
                     <item>Twelue Inches make a Foote.</item>
                     <item>Thrée foote make a Yarde.</item>
                     <item>Fiue yards and a halfe maketh a Pearch, whiche in ſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries men call a Pole or Rod. a Pearche.</item>
                     <item>Foure Pearches make a day worke.</item>
                     <item>Tenne daye workes or fourtie Pearches maketh a rode or <abbr>quart</abbr> of an Acre.</item>
                     <item>Foureſcore Pearches or twoo Roodes maketh halfe an Acre.</item>
                     <item>A hundreth and lx. Perches or twoo Roodes, make an Acre.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And fortie Perches in length, and foure in breadth is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>¶A Generall Rule to be learned of the ſimple, <hi>to caſt Pearches and dayworkes into Acres.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a Marke of Engliſhe money, containeth twoo Nobles, which containe Clx. d. that is euery No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble foure ſcoure pence: &amp; euery halfe Noble xl. <abbr>d</abbr>: So an acre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth Clx. perches, halfe an acre
<pb facs="tcp:7121:50"/>
foure ſcoure Perches, and the quarter of an acre or roode, xl. Perches.</p>
                  <p>And in euery Marke is xl. grotes, and in euerie Grote. iiii. d. ſo is there in euery Acre xl. daye woorkes, and in euery day worke foure Perches.</p>
                  <p>Thus by rate of money, perches and daieworkes are eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reduced into acres: or in this maner alſo euery x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. is thrée quarters of an Acre, and euery pounde in money is one acre and a halfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Jnſtruction for Introduction.</head>
                  <p>TO aunſwere by Rodde or by line, it is at your pleaſure, but of them both the lyne is the ſpedier and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, and alſo of moſt antiquitie.</p>
                  <p>Your line beyng foure Perches of lengthe, and at euery pearche ende a knot, would be well ſeared with hoate Waxe and Roſen, to auoide ſtretching thereof in the wete, and ſhrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the drought.</p>
                  <p>Alſo you muſt note, there are diuerſe faſhions of landes, and therefore diuerſly to be meaſured. And ſome manner of lande lieth in ſuche ſondrie fourmes, that it muſt needes be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not in the whole, but in diuers parcelles, euery parte by it ſelf. Alſo where a pece of Lande is to be deuided into diuers partes, of whiche eche one muſte bee meaſured by hym ſelfe, then ye ought vigilauntly to conſider, into how many parcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls, and into how many and what maner faſhions they muſt be diuided, that ye may meaſure euery parte, accordyng to his fourme or faſhion.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Note alſo that howſoeuer your péece of lande be fourmed or faſhioned, be it ſquare or partly ſquare, rounde or partely rounde, triangled or partly triangled, or a hill mountyng, or a valley deſcending (of ſome of al which figures ye ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſee examples) Yet alwaies muſt ſuche peeces of Lande whatſoeuer it bee, bee reduced into one certaine breadth and one certaine length, or els it can neuer bee collected or ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into a perfecte contente or number of Acres, and other odde quantities. The findyng out of whiche Lengthes and Breadthes, my examples enſuyng ſhall throughly ſhewe you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>¶The firſte Rule, called the Rule of Squares.</head>
                  <p>Now becauſe the euen Squares bee the eaſieſt to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:51"/>
and therefore beſte firſte to bee placed, for the inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of learners, I thought requiſite to beginne firſt with them.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>¶ Example of Squares.</head>
                     <p>SVppoſe your peece of Lande to be ſquare, that is to ſay, equall of breadth at both endes and equall of length at both the ſides, after this figure enſuing, whereof the ſides is, 40. perches a péece of length, and the breadth is 10. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches a peece.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Then is there no more to doe, but the ſame being ſo mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and found, multiply the length with the breadth of the Perches whiche is here. 40. by 10. And being ſo multiplied, it commeth to 400 Perches, whiche if ye ſeeke in the Table hereafter followyng ſet out for contentes (or els doe caſte it into acres, or otherwiſe by rate of money, as in the generall rule aforeſaide is ſhewed you, you ſhal finde that péece to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine 2. Acres. 2. Roodes.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:7121:51"/>And where ſome vnſkilfull meaſurers, vſe to meate a peece of lande rounde about, of whatſoeuer faſhion it bee, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the number of perches of euery ſide together, and then vſe to parte the whole number of Perches, into foure equall portions, of whiche, they will take one parte of the breadth, and the other for the length, thei are not a little deceiued.</p>
                     <p>The ſeconde Rule, called the rule of Triangles.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer, a man maie not onely caſte the ſquares afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied, and all other ſquare lande if he pleaſe (though for ſuch, the rule aforeſaied is the ſpedier) by the rule of Triangles hereafter enſuyng. But alſo there is almoſte no maner of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned lande, but it may by diligence be brought, or deuided into Triangles, and ſo by the Triangle Rule, the iuſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Acres founde and meaſured.</p>
                     <p>Example of peeces of Lande Triangled and firſt of the euen Triangle.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Admitte this Figure enſuyng to be a parcell of Lande, of whiche my deſire is to haue the iuſt and true meaſure.</p>
                     <p>There aboute is written as ye ſee
<pb facs="tcp:7121:52"/>
B C D E. I finde by meaſuryng corde, or ſuche like, that the dependyng, or whipped line B, C, is 24. perches and the baſe line D. E, whiche the dependyng line cutteth in forme of a ſquire, to bee 24. alſo. Then multiplie 24. Perches by halfe the dependyng line, whiche is 12 Perches, and it amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to 288 Perches, whiche ſummed into Acres, make one Acre, three Roodes, and twoo daie woorkes. But for your more ſpede of caſtyng, if you pleaſe, when you haue found the iuſte length, and breadth of any figure, repaire to the Table hereafter deſcribed, and that will ſhewe you the iuſte number of Acres.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>And this is the generall rule of all maner of Triangles, as well preſently hereafter figured, as of all other whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thei bee. Alſo it is the principalleſt rule for meaſuryng of lande.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rules">
                  <head>The Rules for vnequall parcelles of Lande.</head>
                  <p>NOw when any péece of Lande happeneth to bee of ſuche fourme, that it hath many pointes &amp; Corners vnequally fourmed: Then becauſe it is yet neither triangle nor ſquare, it is without the compaſſe of your Rules before ſpecified, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be deuided, as the proportion of the Figures follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng do ſhewe, and ſuche like. Then ye muſt by ſeperation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them into partes, That is to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. 3. 4. or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as cauſe ſhall require, either into triangles or ſquares. And note that firſt. I ſhewe you Figures, of three imagines péeces of Lande, or euer they bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by the ſep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratyng
<pb facs="tcp:7121:54"/>
line, as the examples hereafter doe declare and ſhew. Ye muſt caſt euery parcel triangled or ſquared, by the order of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les afore ſpecified.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <div type="examples">
                     <head>¶ Examples of the ſaile vnequall figures afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide <hi>here as ye ſee nowe ſeparated.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOWE as concernyng theſe Figures afore alſo ſhewed, ye ſee howe nowe they be by the lyne of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion (whiche is the daſhed line) ſeparated or ſeuered, that is to ſay the firſt into one ſquare and
<pb facs="tcp:7121:54"/>
twoo triangles, without the daſhed line. The ſeconde figure into 2. trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, and the thirde into thrée triangles by the daſhed line.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Now the deſcending wip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped line of the 2. triangles at the endes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſquare ſuppoſe to be 6. Perches a péece, &amp; the ſaid ſide whiche they cut ſquarewiſe 10. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, then multiplie either of the ſaid 2. ſides cut ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewiſe, with half the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding lines being 3. a peece, and it maketh either of the ſaid triangles 7. day woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and 3. perches a peece. And ſo the whole ſome of the firſte figure caſte toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is 1. Acre &amp; 2. perches.</p>
                     <p>Nowe ye ſée the ſecond fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by the line daſhed, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the line of ſeparation, to be deuided into 2. parcelles of lande triangled. The ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng line of the vppermoſt whereof, Imagine to be 8
<pb facs="tcp:7121:55"/>
Perches, and the daſhed line whiche it cutteth ſquarewiſe to be 12. Perches. And ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halfe of the depending line beyng 4. multiplied by 12. maketh 1. Roode &amp; 2. day workes. And li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe the dependyng line of the nether parcell of the ſaide fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure is 6. and the baſe line which it deuideth ſquarewiſe. 12. Perches and ſo the halfe of 6. whiche is 3. multiplied by. 12. maketh. 36. Perches, whiche is 9. dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> workes. And ſo the whole péece of lande or figure containeth. 3. Roodes and 1. day worke.</p>
                     <p>And ye ſée the thirde figure is nowe deuided by the twoo daſhed lines of ſeparation into thrée triangles, whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth as in the figure I haue ſet out, without any further rehearſall, for auoyding of tediouſnes.</p>
                     <p>Alſo ſome péeces of Lande as theſe twoo figures enſuyng, and ſuche like, albeit they may be deuided into triangles, and ſo by the Rule of triangles meaſured, yet haue they a proper Rule for the more celeritie in meaſuryng of theim.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>¶The Rule of triangled Squares.</head>
                  <p>ANd for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, the firſte of theſe figures being A.B.C.D. and alſo the other figures beyng E.F.G.H, And all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:55"/>
of others ſuche fourmed péeces of lands, when thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt meaſure them, doe no more but ioygne the endes both in one ſumme, and then take the halfe of that number, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie him with the whole number of the middle lyne or whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped line, and the content<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> appeare, as ye ſhall ſee the firſte figure, at the like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and C. is 4. Perches: and betwene B. and D. is ſixe Perches. Nowe 4. and 6. make 10. The halfe whereof is. 5. whiche beyng multiplied by 10. which is the middle depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding or whipped line, cometh to 50. Perches, whiche maketh one Roode, and two daie woorkes and thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Perches. And ſo call the other figure alſo and ſuche li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>
                     <hi>¶The moſt excellent Rule for meaſuryng of</hi> Wood Lande, and other peeces of Lande, that are deformed or on all ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnequall.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touchyng the meaſuring of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſuche like: And alſo for any maner of euill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auoured faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned péece of Lande, which requireth to be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many Squares or Triangles, To ſaue labour, ye may do as followeth: alſo it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> (this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le following) where a man cannot vewe euerie waie from ſide to ſide, for ſtanding of Wood, Fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> or ſuche like.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>And againe briefly for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, this is the ſaid laſt Rule. Firſte by enlargemente meaſure it Square. Then multiplie the one ſide with the other, and cut of the totall or producte, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll awaie that ye added and the true meaſure is contained in the remainder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The Rule of Roundes <hi>or Circles.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND nowe for meaſuryng of a Peece of Lande all rounde, whiche is without any Angle or Square: or euer ye can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eate ſuche a peece of Lande, I muſte aduertiſe you of certaine proper names, belongyng to a Circle, or Rounde peece of Lande, how euery parte is called properly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:7121:56"/>A circle doeth containe theſe partes, which are alſo called by theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuyng.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Roundell is called the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</item>
                     <item>The iuſte middle pointe or pricke therein is called the Center.</item>
                     <item>The line goyng through the pricke or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and iuſtly deuidyng the circle, is called the Diameter.</item>
                     <item>The halfe of that is called the ſemidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                     <item>The part deuided aboue in the circle, from A to B is called an Arke.</item>
                  </list>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>And then if ye would knowe, what this rounde peece of Lande followyng containeth: Take this for a generall rule, in euery Diameter multiplie halfe the circumference, and it ſheweth the content of any circle.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>An example of partes and portions of a Circle.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Magine that P. Q. R. here enſuyng, were a parte of a Circle, or peece of Lande, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ye would haue. And the whole compaſſe of the Circle, whiche this portion repreſenteth, as is ſaid before, were 80. Perches, his breadth
<pb facs="tcp:7121:57"/>
or Diameter is 40. Perches: The compaſſe whipped arke, vnto the middle line, whiche deuideth the Center, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Diameter, is
<figure>
                           <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                        </figure>
40. Perches: now the ſemidiameter, or halfe breadth of the Circle 20. multiplie halfe the Compaſſe of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference whipped, and it maketh twoo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres and a halfe, and that is the contente of the whipped compaſſe to the ſides of the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles whipped. Now to vnderſtande the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther portion, or arke that is aboue the whipped Triangles, ſeuered by the line P. R. ye ſhall adde the contente of the Triangles, whiche is one Acre and three roodes to be found by the rule of Triangles: ſo haue you in the whole fower A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres and one roode. This ſumme ſubtracted from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber contained in the whole Circle: the remain is the ſumme of thoſe Perches contained in the Arke, or ſmall péece aboue the Triangles, that is to ſay, three roodes, and that added to the reſte, maketh the whole Circle fiue Acres againe, as is aforeſaide.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>The rule of Reguler ſquared lande.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT and if your compaſſe bée a peece of Reguler, or right ſquared lande of many ſides, as are theſe two figures enſuing: Then meaſure and laie al the ſides together, taking the halfe number of perches there contained. Then drawe a right depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng line from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of one of the ſides to the Center, and with that breadth
<pb facs="tcp:7121:58"/>
multiplie the other halfe number aforeſaied, and the content will appeare.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>Admitte this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<figure>
                           <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                        </figure>
A. D. B. C. to be a parcell of Land ſixe ſquared, and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of the ſides to bee 20. Perches a pece, the whiche ſummed together make 120 Perches, the halfe whereof is 60. and the depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped line, commyng from the middeſt of the vpper ſquare to the Center to be 30. whiche twoo ſummes multiplied one by the other, as afore is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, make fiue Acres, twoo roodes, and fiue daies woorke, and in like maner the other Figure is to be caſte, or els if ye liſte not to multiplie the ſommes your ſelfe, you maie with the lengthe and breadth, enter my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enſuyng.</p>
                     <p>And note this alſo principally, that triangles of all ſides alike, and alſo the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate
<pb facs="tcp:7121:58"/>
figure, maie be alſo meaſured by this Rule.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>
                     <hi>¶The Rule for meaſuryng of Mountaynes</hi> or Mountaine Lande, and alſo valeys or valley grounde.</head>
                  <p>NOw for the mountaine or hille, ye muſt doe this. Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Circuite of the Baſe or foote of the Hill or Mountaine, and that done, meaſure the vpper parte, toppe, or Summitie therof. Then ioyne theim or adde theim together. So muſt you likewiſe doe of the Aſſenſes, that is to ſay, of the going vp from the foote to the toppe, alwaies ioynyng the meaſures of the ſhorter and lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in one ſumme. Then take the one halfe of the Aſcences ioyned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with multiplie the halfe of the circuites added, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will appeare: as for example.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Suppoſe E. F. G. to be the Mountaine or Hille, The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the foote or baſe whereof, I finde by meaſure to bee 400. Perches. G. the Toppe to be. 20. Perches, F. and G. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the Aſſenſes to be 60. perches, &amp; the other Aſſents from E to G. to be. 38. Perches. Now when I haue added to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:7121:59"/>
the Circuite of the baſe or foote, and the Circuite of the Summitie or toppe, I finde, they make. 420. The halfe whereof is. 210. And the halfe of both the Aſſenſes to be. 49. Perches, whiche twoo Summes of the ſaide halfes, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the one into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, or if ye enter for ſpéede, the Table with thoſe Summes, ye ſhall finde they make iuſt. 64. Acres. 1. roode. 2. daye workes, 2 Perches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND moreouer, now for the Valley or Dale, looke as in the Mountaine ye meaſured the circuite of the foote or baſe: So now here the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of the height of the Valley muſt be meaſured, and alſo as ye ſought to haue the meaſure there of the Sum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ity or toppe: So muſt ye here alſo meaſure the Circuite of the Bottome, or Déepth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as in the Mountaine, ye meaſured the Aſſenſe or goyng vp to the toppe: So muſte here, the Deſcenſe or going downe of the hill be meaſured. And then for woorkyng the reſidue, doe like as I haue in meaſuryng the Mountaine enfourmed you.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>¶An example of meaſuryng the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alley.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND becauſe I will ſhewe you but one example for all: I haue here figured a péece of Lande of an vnequall Valley, that it maye bee the Rule of meaſuryng of all manner of Valleis, in what fourme ſoeuer they lye or be faſhioned. Laie the circuite of the heighte whiche I ſuppoſe here to be 30. in the compaſſe aboute of the toppe of the Valley. And the déepth of the Valley beeyng 16. Perches, and take theſe for the breadth. Then meaſure the Deſcences of both ſides to the bottome, the one ſide whereof here is. 18. and the other. 34. perches, whiche added together make 52. And that is for the length. And then multiply halfe the ſaied number whiche is. 26. by 46. Perches, beeyng halfe the other number afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide,
<pb facs="tcp:7121:59"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>diagram</figDesc>
                        </figure>
and it cometh to 1196. Perches, whiche make the contente of the Valley aforeſaide. 7. Acres. 1. Roode and. 9. daye workes. Now if ye liſt not your ſelfe to caſt this ſumme, and all ſuche like ſummes, euer when ye haue the length and breadth of any of all the figures aforeſaied or any other like. Enter the Table following for your expedition, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes will appeare.</p>
                     <p>And thus muche as is afore for the Introduction of meaſuryng Lande, with the practiſe, ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Surueiour, or his diligent Lande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meater.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
